Mod f- x- square d- x.
对FX的平方取余  结果是DX
So please finish Percival for next time.
下次上课前请做完
I know many of you had this as undergraduates but it won't hurt to brush up.
大学时虽已学过  但复习无妨
Thank you Steven.
谢谢  史蒂芬
I also put an advanced Fourier system on the main hallway chalkboard.
走廊黑板上有高级傅立叶算式
I'm hoping that one of you might prove it by the end of the semester.
希望学期结束前有人会解
Now the person to do so will not only be in my good graces...
解出来的人不只有好成绩
but also go on to fame and fortune by having their accomplishment recorded and their name printed.
还可因此纪录名利双收
in the auspicious M.I.T. Tech.
留名麻省理工学院
Former winners include Nobel laureates Field's medal winners...
之前解答包括诺贝尔得主  菲尔德奖章得主
renowned astrophysicists...
天文物理学家
and lowly M.I.T. professors.
还有卑贱的麻省理工教授
Well that's all. If you have any questions...
就这样  如果有问题
I'm sure that Tom has the answers.
我相信汤姆会解答
Hi Will.
威尔
Kirsten how you doing?
你好吗?
I'm all right. How are you?
很好  你呢?
Good.
好
I didn't get on Cathy last night.
我昨晚没上凯西
- No?  - No.
- 没有?  - 没有
Why not?
为什么?
I don't know. Cathy!
不知道  凯西!
What?
干嘛?
Why didn't you give me none of that nasty little hoochie- woochie...
为什么不让我爽
- you usually throw at me?  - Oh fuck you...
- 就像平时那样?  - 去你的
and your Irish curse Chuckie.
还有你的爱尔兰脏话
Like I'd waste my energy spreadin' my legs for that Tootsie Roll dick?
我才不要为了小老二张开腿
Go home and give it a tug yourself.
回家自己打手枪去吧
Tootsie Roll!
小老二!
T- Toots!
She's missin' a tooth Will.
她少一颗牙
She's got skin problems. I don't...
她皮肤也有问题
Plus it's like 5- to- 2 Morgan ends up marryin' her you know what I mean?
况且到头来摩根八成会娶她
There's only so many times you can bang your friend's future wife. It's wrong.
朋友的准老婆只能上几次
Where you goin'?
你去哪?
I'm gonna take off.
我要走了
Fuck you you're takin' off. It's like what 10:00?
我操  才十点就要走?
No I'm tired.
我累了
Irish curse?
爱尔兰脏话?
She don't know. There ain't no Irish curse.
你懂什么?
Out! Stop pressuring me back.
别老故意打到我
Stop crowding the plate!
不要再靠近本垒板
Which one will it be?
你选哪个?
You're gonna get charged you know that?
你会被起诉  你知道吗?
You think I'm afraid of you you big fuck?
你以为我怕你啊?
You're crowdin' the fuckin' plate.
是你他妈的太靠近本垒板
Hey uh Casey's bouncin' up a bar at Harvard next week.
盖西下礼拜会在哈佛的酒吧
We should go up there.
我们应该去
What are we gonna do up there?
到那边干嘛
I don't know.
不知道
We'll fuck up some smart kids. Probably fit right in.
去整聪明小孩  你很擅长
Ow! Fuckin' punk.
臭痞子
- Oh what's up? You still tough?  - Come on!
- 怎样?  你很凶吗?  - 来啊!
Come on. Come on. That's it.
来啊  对  约翰  来啊
- Professor Lambeau?  - Yes?
- 蓝勃教授?  - 是的
I'm in your applied theories class. We're all up at the math and science building.
我是你的应用理论课学生
Come here.
过来
It's Saturday.
今天礼拜六
Unless you wanna have a drink with me tonight.
除非你今晚陪我喝酒
Maybe.
或许吧
We just couldn't wait until Monday to find out.
但我们急着想弄清楚
Find out what?
弄清楚什么?
Who proved the theorem.
是谁解出傅立叶算式
This is correct.
完全正确
Who did this? Jack?
谁解的?  杰克?
It wasn't me.
不是我
Nemesh?
尼米许?
N- No way.
怎么可能
Come on Joey now!
快  乔依  就是现在!
Billy McNamara's up.
他快没力了  把他干掉
Come on kid!
快点!
Joey dig it out! Dig it out!
乔依  快跑
Bring it down Mac! That's how to do it!
快放下  这样才对
Attaboy! Take two Mac.
做得好  二垒  往二垒跑
Hey Morgan who's the girl with the striped pants? She's got a nice ass.
穿条纹裤的俏屁股女人是谁?
Yeah that's a real nice ass.
那屁股真不赖
Who's the guy she's with?
她跟谁一起?
That fuckin' guinea. I hate that little bitch.
是他妈的卡迈  我讨厌他
Will knows him.
威尔认识他
Yeah I do.
你认识他?
Yeah fuckin' Carmine Scarpaglia.
对  该死的卡迈
That guy used to beat the shit out of me in kindergarten.
他幼稚园时把我揍得好惨
That guy?
那个人?
Yeah.
恩
Fuck this. Let's get some food.
操他妈的  去弄点东西吃吧
Oh what Morgan you're not gonna go talk to her?
摩根  你不跟她讲话吗?
Fuck her.
去她的
I could go for a Whopper.
我宁可吃大汉堡
Let's go to Kelly's.
到凯利去吧
Morgan I'm not goin' to Kelly's.
才不要去
Just 'cause you like the take- out girl.
你只是喜欢那儿的外卖女孩
It's 15 minutes out of our way.
而且要多绕15分钟路
What the fuck are we gonna do? We can't spare 15 minutes?
我们他妈的挪不出15分钟吗?
Double burger.
大汉堡
Chuck I had a double burger.
查克  我有个大汉堡
Would you shut the fuck up! I know what you ordered. I was there.
闭嘴  我知道你点什么
So give me my fuckin' sandwich.
那就把我的三明治给我
What do you mean your sandwich? I bought it.
什么叫你的三明治?  是我买的
Morgan how much money you got on you?
你身上有多少钱?
I said I'd get change when I get the snow cone.
买霜淇淋就会有零钱了嘛
I said that when we pulled up. Give me my sandwich and stop bein' a prick.
汉堡给我  别这么讨厌
All right well give me your fuckin' 16 cents that you got on you now.
好  把身上的一毛六给我
We'll put your fuckin' sandwich on layaway.
我让你他妈的分期付款买汉堡
Here we go. Keep it right up here for ya.
汉堡摆这边
We'll put you on a program.
我们让你分期付款
Every day you come in here with your six cents.
每天六分钱
At the end of the week you get your sandwich.
周末给你汉堡
Are you gonna be an asshole?
你怎么这么混蛋?
What am I fuckin' sandwich welfare?
你他妈的以为我卖慈济汉堡啊
I think you should establish a good line of credit.
你应该建立良好信用
Like how you bought your couch...payment plans.
对  就像你们买沙发那样
Remember how your mother brought in ten dollars every day for a year?
记得你妈每天存十块钱吗?
She finally got her couch Rent- A- Center style.
最后她终于买到沙发了
Can I have my food please?
可以把食物给我了吗?
Here's your fuckin' double burger.
把你的大汉堡拿去
Hey hold up Chuck.
等等  查克
Slow it down.
慢下来
Who do we got?
怎么了?
I don't know yet.
还不知道
Come on Will.
算了  威尔
We seen the guy 15 minutes ago.
15分钟前才在公园看到他
We should've fight him then. We're eatin' our snacks now.
要扁他当时就该扁了
Shut up Morgan you're goin'.
闭嘴  摩根  你也下去
I'm not goin'.
我才不去
So don't go.
那就别去
I'm not goin'.
我不去
Fuckin' go Morgan.
你他妈的给我去  摩根
Let me tell you somethin'. If you're not out there in two fuckin' seconds
我跟你讲  两秒内不滚出去
when I'm done with them you're next.
等我扁完他们  就扁你
Carmine it's me Will. Remember?
卡迈  是我  威尔  记得吗?
We went to kindergarten together.
我们是幼稚园同学
- Fuckin' let's go man.  - Step on his fuckin' head.
- 他在干嘛?  - 他把他扁惨了
Get his ass on the ground. Stop that motherfucker.
叫那家伙住手
Motherfucker die!
混蛋  去死吧!
Will! Will come on!
威尔  条子  快走
Will come on. Let's go. Let's go.
条子...快
Easy brother easy.
别激动  别激动
Hey fellas thanks for comin' out.
怎么样?  谢谢你们出来
Come here!
过来!
Ah. Fuck.
操
Is it just my imagination or has my class grown considerably?
这是做梦还是班级变大了?
Well by no stretch of my imagination...
如果不是在做梦的话...
do I believe you've all come here to hear me lecture.
你们是来听我讲课
Rather to ascertain the identity of the mystery math magician.
或想知道神秘数学奇才是谁
So without further adieu come forward silent rogue and receive thy prize.
沉默的天才  出来领奖吧
Well I'm sorry to disappoint my spectators but...
抱歉让观众失望了
it seems there will be no unmasking here today.
看来今天不会揭晓了
However uh my colleagues and l have conferred...
我和同事决定再下战帖
and there is a problem on the board right now...
外面黑板上有个题目
that took us more than two years to prove.
我们花了两年时间才解开
So let this be said: The gauntlet has been thrown down...
请沉默的天才再解解看
but the faculty have answered and answered with vigor.
全体教授已备有解答
Hey when's the arraignment?
几时提讯?
Next week.
下星期
Sorry.
对不起
What are you doing?
你在做什么?
Sorry.
对不起
That's people's work. You can't graffiti here.
你不能在人家的方程式上涂鸦
Don't you walk away from me!
你别走!
Hey fuck you!
去你的!
Oh you're a clever one. What's your name?
别耍聪明  你叫什么名字?
Oh my God.
我的天
Looks right.
好像是对的
Will how retarded do you gotta be to get fired from that job?
要多智障才会被开除?
I mean how hard is it to push a motherfuckin' broom around?
在屋子里扫地有那么难吗?
Mitch you got fired from pushin' a fuckin' broom.
你连扫地都会被开除
I got fired 'cause management was restructuring.
那是因为管理阶层重组
Yeah restructuring the amount of retards they had workin' for 'em.
对  重组智障儿的数量
Shut up. You get canned more than tuna bitch.
闭嘴  你被开除的次数更多
At least I got a motherfuckin' job right now don't I?
起码现在我有工作
Yeah.
是啊
Why'd you get fired Will? Come on.
威尔  你为何被开除?
Management was restructuring.
管理阶级重组
My uncle could probably get you on a demo team.
我舅舅或许能给你工作
Can he do that?
可以吗?
You kiddin' me! I asked you yesterday if I could get a job.
你耍我  我昨天还问过你
And I told you "no" yesterday.
我昨天告诉你不行
- What's up Casey?  - What's up Case?  - What's up Big Case?
怎么样?  盖斯
Let's sit over here.
坐这边
Oh this is...this is a Harvard bar huh?
这就是哈佛酒吧?
I thought there'd be like equations and shit on the wall.
我以为墙上会有方程式呢
I will take a pitcher of the finest lager in the house.
我要一壶店里最好的啤酒
Timeout.
暂停
I'm gonna have to bust a little move on them Harvard hotties down there at the bar.
我要去泡吧台的哈佛辣妹
- Work some magic.  - Get some potion for us.
- 看我的吧  - 帮我们钓几个
- Oh hello.  - Oh hello.
- 你好  - 你好
Hi. How are ya?
你好吗?
Fine.
好
So do you ladies uh...
两位美女...
Come here often?
常来吗?
Do I come here? I come here a bit.
我常来吗?  我...
I'm here you know from time to time.
偶尔来
Do you go to school here?
你们在这儿念书
Yep.
对
Yeah that's it. I think I had a class with you.
就是嘛  我想我跟你同班
Oh yeah. What class?
是吗?  哪一班?
History.
历史
Maybe.
或许
Yes I think that's what it was.
应该没错
You don't necessarily...may not remember me. You know I like it here.
你可能不认识我  我来这边来
It doesn't mean 'cause I go here I'm a genius. I am very smart.
并不表示我是天才  但我还是很聪明
Hey how's it goin'? How are ya?
你好吗?
Good. How ya doin'?
好  你呢?
What class did you say that was?
你说你在哪一班?
History.
历史
Just history? It must have been a survey course then.
历史?  那一定是概论课程
Yeah it was. It was surveys.  - Right.
- 对  是概论课程  - 没错
You should check it out. It's a good course. It'd be a good class.
你应该上上看  不错的课
How'd you like that course?
你觉得那堂课怎么样?
You know frankly I found that class you know rather elementary.
老实说  我觉得很基础
Elementary.
基础
You know I don't doubt that it was.
肯定是的
I uh I remember that class.
我记得那堂课了
It was um... It was just between recess and lunch.
就在休息和午餐之间
Clark why don't you go away?
克拉克  你走开啦
Why don't you relax?
放轻松点
Why don't you go away?
走开啦
I'm just havin' fun with my new friend.
我跟我的新朋友很开心
Are we gonna have a problem?
有什么问题吗?
No no no no. There's no problem here.
没问题
I was just hoping you might give me some insight into the evolution...
只是想请教你对于市场经济...
of the market economy in the southern colonies.
在南部殖民地发展的看法
My contention is that prior to the Revolutionary War...
我主张在革命战争前...
the economic modalities especially in the southern colonies...
南方殖民地的经济形态...
could most aptly be characterized as...
最适切被刻画为...
- agrarian precapitalist.  - Let me tell you somethin'.
- 农地  - 让我来说两句
Of course that's your contention. You're a first- year grad student.
那当然是你的论点  新生嘛
You just got finished readin' some Marxian historian... Pete Garrison probably...
才刚念完马克斯主义
You're gonna be convinced of that till next month when you get to James Lemon.
下个月念到雷蒙的论点你会更深信不疑
Then you're gonna be talkin' about how the economies of Virginia and Pennsylvania...
然后你会谈到维吉尼亚州及宾州...
were entrepreneurial and capitalist way back in 1740.
在1740年如何企业化与资本主义化...
That's gonna last until next year. You're gonna be in here regurgitatin' Gordon Wood...
一直持续到明年你反刍伍德...
talkin' about you know the prerevolutionary utopia...
大谈革命前乌托邦...
and the capital- forming effects of military mobilization.
和军事动员对资本形成的影响
Well as a matter of fact I won't.
事实上我反对这个观点
Because Wood drastically underestimates the impact of...
因为伍德完全低估了社会...
Wood drastically underestimates the impact of social distinctions...
伍德低估了财富的社会差异...
predicated upon wealth especially inherited wealth.
尤其是继承财富
You got that from Vickers
这是你从维克斯读到的论点
Work in Essex County. Page 98 right?
艾群就业分析  98页  对不对?
I read that too.
我也读过
Were you gonna plagiarize the whole thing for us?
你要剽窃整本书吗?
Do you have any thoughts of your own on this matter?
对这些论点你有个人想法吗?
Or is that your thing? You come into a bar. You read some obscure passage.
你跑到酒吧来高谈书中的论点
Then pretend... pawn it off as your own.
还假装是自己的观点
As your own idea just to impress some girls? Embarrass my friend?
就为了泡妞  糗我朋友吗?
See the sad thing about a guy like you is in 50 years
你的可悲是在五十年后
you're gonna start doin' some thinkin' on your own.
你才会开始了解
You're gonna come up with the fact that there are two certainties in life.
生命中有两件事是确定的
One: Don't do that.
一是别只会打高空
And two: You dropped 150 grand on a fuckin' education...
二是你花一万五所受的教育...
you could've got for $1.50 in late charges at the public library.
用一块五就能在图书馆得到
Yeah but I will have a degree.
对  但我会有文凭
And you'll be servin' my kids fries at a drive...
你却只能在我去滑雪胜地途中...
through on our way to a skiing trip.
卖薯条给我的小孩
Maybe but at least I won't be unoriginal.
或许吧  起码我不会抄袭逼别人的
If you have a problem with that we could step outside. We could figure it out.
不爽可以到外面解决
No man there's no problem. It's cool.
不  没事  很酷
It's cool?
酷?
Damn right it's cool.
你他妈的酷毙了
How do you like me now?
现在喜欢我了吧
My boy's wicked smart.
那小子聪明绝顶
I just spent three minutes in this fuckin' place and run into a barney huh?
才来三分钟就摆平一个傻蛋
There it is.
我来  有了
- Nice to meet you.  - They were fine man.
- 吉米  你好  - 她们可真棒
I was gonna close the deal but then Chuck...Billy insulted one of 'em...
我们差点就要把到她们  结果比利触怒她们
The heavyset girl said I had a receding hairline and I was a few pounds overweight.
辣妹就说我头快秃了  又太胖
And I was like "Go fuck yourself."
我就说"去你妈的"
I swallowed a bug.
我什么都没说
You're an idiot.
你是个白痴
What?
什么
You're an idiot.
你是个白痴
I've been sitting over there for 45 minutes...
我坐在那边整整45分钟...
waiting for you to come and talk to me.
等你过来搭讪
But I'm tired now and I have to go home.
但我累了  我得回家了
I couldn't sit there anymore waiting for you.
我不能再坐着等你
I'm Will.
我是威尔
Skylar.
史凯兰
- Skylar.  - Oh and by the way
- 史凯兰  - 对了
that guy over there... Michael Bolton clone...
那个人  迈可波顿二号
He wasn't sitting with us so to speak.
跟我们不是一国的
- I know. I kinda got that impression.  - Good. Okay.
- 我知道  我看得出来  - 那就好
Well I've got to go.
我得走了
Gotta get up early and waste some more money on my overpriced education.
我要早起花钱买文凭
No I didn't mean you.
我不是指你
That's all right.
没关系
There's my number. Maybe we can go out for coffee sometime.
这是我的电话  也许有空可以喝杯咖啡
All right yeah. Maybe we can just get together and eat a bunch of caramels.
好  或许聚在一起吃焦糖
What do you mean?
什么意思?
When you think about it it's as arbitrary as drinkin' coffee.
那和喝咖啡一样惬意
Oh. Yeah. Okay.
是吗
Uh right then.
好的
Yo!
兄弟们!
- Fuck you bitch!  - Fuck you.
- 去你的!  - 我才去你的
There goes them fuckin' barneys right now with his skiin' trip.
那些傻旁谀潜
Hold on.
等等
We should've beat that old bitch's ass.
我们应该扁那个混蛋
Do you like apples?
你喜欢青苹果甜甜圈吗?
- Yeah.  - Yeah?
- 是的  - 喜欢?
Well I got her number!
我得到她的电话
How do you like them apples?
你却只能吃甜甜圈
Come.
来
Excuse me? Is this the Buildings and Grounds office?
打扰了  这是大楼管理室吗?
Yeah. What can I do for you?
有何贵干
I just need the name of a student who works here.
我要找个在这里打工的学生
No students work for me.
没学生替我做事
Could you please check?
请你查一下
I have this guy who works in my building. He's about this high.
有个人在我那栋楼做事  大概长这么高
Which one is your building?
你在几号楼?
- Two.  - Two. Building two.
- 二  - 二号楼
Look if anything was stolen I should know about it.
如果有东西失窃我该知道
No it's nothing like that.
不是那样
I just need his name.
我只是要找他
I can't give you his name unless you have a complaint.
除非你投诉  否则不告诉你
This is Professor Lambeau.
这位是蓝勃教授
And this is Professor Hayes.
这位是海斯教授
Tom please.
汤姆  拜托
This is important. Please.
这很重要  拜托
Will didn't show for work today.
威尔今天没上班
Got this job through his P.O. You can call him.
他透过PO找到这份工作  你可以打给他
P.O.?
Yeah. Parole officer.
对  观护人
Thank you.
谢谢
Asshole.
混蛋
There is a lengthy legal precedent Your Honor going back to 1789
法官先生  这溯及1789年的司法判例
whereby a defendant can claim self- defense against an agent of the government...
被告可对政府单位要求自卫权
if that act is deemed a defense against tyranny a defense of liberty.
如果该举动是为保护自由  抗拒暴政制裁的话
Your Honor Henry Ward Beecher in Proverbs from the Plymouth Pulpit 1887 said quote...
法官先生  比彻尔在1887年说过
- 1887? This is the 20th century.  - Excuse me. Excuse me.
- 1887?  现在20世纪了  - 抱歉
He's gonna make a mockery.
他在嘲弄法庭
I am afforded the right to speak in my own defense sir.
宪法赋与我为自己辩护之权
By the Constitution of the United States. This guarantees my liberty.
同时宪法还赋予我自由的权力
Don't tell me about the Constitution.
不用你教我宪法条例
"Liberty  " in case you've forgotten is a soul's right to breathe.
自由是一个人呼吸的权利
When it cannot take a long breath laws are girded too tight.
无法让人呼吸的法律太严肃
Without liberty man is a syncope.
不自由  人就是行尸走肉
Man is a what?
什么?
Ibid. Your Honor.
出处同前  法官先生
Son my turn. I've been sitting here for ten minutes...
轮到我  我在这坐了十分钟...
now lookin' over this rap sheet of yours. I just can't believe it.
看着你的罪状  我不敢相信
June '93 assault. September '93 assault.
93年6月  9月故意伤害
Grand theft auto February of '94.
偷车  94年2月
Where apparently you defended yourself and had the case thrown out by citing...
你引述  马与马车的财产权
"free property rights of horse and carriage" from 1798.
并以自我辩护让此案驳回
Joke. January '95 impersonating an officer.
真可笑  95年1月  扮成警察
Mayhem theft resisting. All overturned.
伤害  窃盗  拒捕  全驳回
I'm also aware that you've been through several foster homes.
我知道你住过几个寄养家庭
The state removed you from three because of serious physical abuse.
因受虐而从其中三个搬出
You know another judge might care.
别的法官是关心你
But you hit a cop. You're going in.
但你打警察  就得坐牢
Motion to dismiss is denied. $50  000 bail.
不准提出抗告  保释金五万
Thank you.
谢谢
Rise.
起立
Hello?
喂?
Uh Skylar?
史凯兰?
Hey uh it's Will.
我是威尔
- Who?  - It's Will.
- 谁?  - 威尔
You know the really funny good- looking guy you met at the bar the other night.
你前两天在酒吧碰到的帅哥
I don't recall meeting anyone who matches that description. I think I'd remember.
我不记得有碰到这样的人
Oh all right you got me. It's the ugly obnoxious toothless loser...
好吧  是那个丑陋无比又没牙...
who got hammered and wouldn't leave you alone all night.
还整夜缠着你不放的废物
Oh Will! I remember.
威尔!  我记起来了
How are you? I was wondering if you'd call me.
你好  我还在想你会不会打来
Yeah look I was wondering...
我一直在想...
Yo what's up baby?
怎么样?  宝贝
Hold on one second.
稍等
What you doing? Want some of my ass?
怎样?  宝贝  想上我吗?
Herve I remember you from juvi. How you doing?
赫芙  我记得你  在少年监狱见过  你好吗?
What you doing?
干嘛?  去你的
Oh yeah sorry about that.
对不起
I was wonderin' maybe we could get together sometime this week.
我在想...也许这礼拜可以聚一聚
Sit out at a cafe. Maybe have some caramels.
坐在咖啡座吃点焦糖
Oh that sounds wonderful.
听起来很棒
Yeah?
可以吗?
Yeah sure. Where are you?
可以  你在哪里?
Uh well actually this is just a shot in the dark...
我站的地方有点糟...
but uh there's no chance that you're pre- law is there?
你那儿总不会是看守所吧
Have a seat.
坐
Thank you.
谢谢
Nice talking to ya.
很高兴跟你讲话
What the fuck do you want?
你他妈的想干嘛?
I'm Gerald Lambeau.
我是杰洛蓝勃
Professor you told to fuck himself.
你叫他滚蛋的那个教授
Well what the fuck do you want?
找我干嘛?
I've spoken to the judge.
我跟法官谈过
And he's agreed to release you under my supervision.
他同意在我监护之下  放你出去
Really?
真的?
Yeah.
是的
Under two conditions.
但有两个条件
What are those?
哪两个?
First condition is that you meet with me every week.
第一  你每周要跟我碰面
What for?
做什么?
Go over the proof you're working on.
和你讨论数学
Get into some more advanced...combinatorial mathematics.
看你做些更高级的...组合数学
Finite math.
有限数学
Sounds like a real hoot.
好像很有趣
And the second condition is that...that you see a therapist.
第二  你要看心理医生
I'm responsible to submit reports on those meetings.
由我每周负责作评估报告
If you fail to meet with any of those conditions...
如果你不及格...
you will have to serve time.
照样送你回来坐牢
All right. I'll do the math but I'm not gonna meet with any fuckin' therapist.
好  数学我接受  但我不看去他妈的心理医生
It's better than spending that time in jail isn't it?
这总比蹲牢房好  不是吗?
I read your book.
我看过你的书
And "Mike" was havin' the same problems...
你提到有个病人麦克的问题...
that "Chad  " the stockbroker was havin'.
事实上和证券营业员查克一样
Absolutely right. Right on the button. Good for you Will.
说得很准  很好
Very nice.
非常好
Thank you.
谢谢
Will the pressures...and I'm not judging them.
威尔  有关压力...
I'm not labeling them.
我不是武断地贴你标签
But they are destroying your potential.
但它破坏了你的潜力
No more shenanigans. No more tomfoolery. No more ballyhoo.
别再恶作剧  耍蠢  吹擂
You're right.
你说得对
God I know.
天哪  我知道
You're not gonna get off that easily. Come on Will. A bit more.
要摆脱不容易  来  多讲点
Well I mean I do do things you know?
我有做过一些事
What...What kind of things?
哪种事?
I do things that you know I mean I hide from people.
我做过...你知道...我躲避人群
You hide do you?
你躲避?
No no. I mean I like... I go places. I interact.
不  我也去一些地方交朋友
Really? What sort of places?
真的?  哪种地方
Just certain clubs.
一些酒吧
More. That's nice. Yes. What sort of clubs?
再来  很好  哪种酒吧?
Like uh like Fantasy.
像是"幻想"
Fantasy.
还不错的地方
that's nice. A bit more.
好  说下去
It's something like when you get in there the music like owns you.
一进去整个人就被音乐包围
It's like that house music. It's like...Bom- bom- bom
浩势音乐  砰...
You know you start dancin'. It's just...
你就会开始跳舞...
Yes.
是的
Do you find it hard to hide the fact that you're gay?
隐瞒你是同性恋很难吗?
What are you talking about? What?
你在说什么?
Look buddy.
兄弟
Two seconds ago you were ready to give me a jump.
两秒前你准备扑向我
A jump? Are you...
扑?  你...
I'm terribly sorry to disappoint you.
很抱歉让你失望了  威尔
Hey I don't have a problem with it. I don't care if you putt from the rough.
没关系  我不在乎你从后面上
What are you...P...Putting from the rough? What on earth are you talking about?
从后面上你?  你在讲什么?
A difficult theorem could be like a symphony. It's very erotic.
困难的定理就像性感的交响曲
You go somewhere else. I can't handle this.
你找别人  我应付不来
Thank you Henry.
亨利
Hi Gerry. You know something? I can't do this pro bono work anymore.
我不能再做这种公众服务
It's just not...It's not worth it.
不值得
What happened?
怎么了?
Well I'm going on national television next week.
我要上电视
I mean I haven't got time to tell you much less talk to that raving looney in there.
没空告诉你  更别提这个胡言乱语的疯子
An absolute lunatic he is.
他肯定是疯了
Henry.
亨利
Okay you are in your bed Will.
好  你在你床上
Now how old are you?
你几岁?
Seven.
七岁
What do you see?
你看到什么?
Something's in my room.
我房里有东西
What is it?
是什么?
It's like a...It's a figure. It's hoverin' over me.
是个人形  在我头上盘旋
You are in a safe place Will.
你在安全的地方  威尔
It's t...It's touchin' me.
下面  他在摸我
Where is it touching you?
他摸你哪里?
It's touching me down there
摸我那下面
And I'm nervous.
我很紧张
You don't have to be nervous Will.
不必紧张
We start dancin' and dancin'. It's just beautiful.
我们开始跳舞  好美
'cause we can make a lot of love before the sun goes down.
因为日落前可以做爱
Skyrockets in flight
烟火飞舞
Afternoon delight
午后欢乐
Jesus.
老天
I'm sorry Rich.
抱歉
Come on Rich!
来  瑞克  我们跳舞
I have better things to do with my time.
我有更重要的事情要做
Come on! One dance!
一支舞就好了嘛!
You really hypnotized me you know?
你把我催眠了
For God's sake Will.
看在老天份上  威尔
What? Oh come on. He left. You can't pin that on me.
干嘛?  他走了不能怪我
I told you to cooperate with these people.
你得跟这些人合作
Look...
看着...
into my eyes.
我的眼睛
Get out Will.
出去
I don't need therapy.
我不需要治疗
That's enough. Get out!
够了  出去!
I called Mel Weintraub this morning to see...
我早上打过电话给梅尔...
Oh what's the use?
有用吗?
What do you want to do?
你想怎么做?
Well there's someone.
有个人
Who is he?
是谁?
He used to be my uh... my roommate in college.
他是我大学室友
Trust. Very important in a relationship.
信任
It's also very important in a clinical situation.
在感情上和临床上都很重要
Why is trust the most important thing...
为何信任对于突破患者心防...
in making a breakthrough with a client?
是最重要的关键?
Maureen stop the oral fixation for a moment and join us.
莫琳  别老张着嘴  听课
Vinnie.
维尼
Because uh... Trust is uh... Trust is life.
因为信任就是生命
Wow. That's very deep. Thank you Vinnie.
很深奥  谢谢你
Next time get the notes from your brother.
你抄你弟弟的笔记吗?
No.
没有
If a patient doesn't feel safe enough trust you.
若病患不信任你
Then they won't be honest with you.
就不会坦诚相对
Then there's really no point for them being in therapy.
治疗对他们来说就毫无意义
I mean hey if they don't trust you you're never gonna get them to sleep with you.
不信任你就不会跟你上床
That should be the goal of any good therapist.
那该是心理医生的最终目的
Nail 'em while they're vulnerable. That's my motto.
趁脆弱时下手  我的座右铭
Oh good everyone's back. Welcome back everybody.
很好  大家都醒了  欢迎回来
Hello Sean.
你好  尚恩
Hey Gerry.
杰洛
Um ladies and gentlemen we are in the presence of greatness.
现在介绍一个大人物给各位
Professor Gerald Lambeau.
杰洛蓝勃教授
Field's medal winner for combinatorial mathematics.
组合数学的菲尔德奖章得主
Anyone know what the Field's medal is?
谁知道什么是菲尔德奖章?
It's a really big deal. It's like the Nobel prize for math.
了不起  数学界的诺贝尔奖
Except they only give it out once every four years.
只是它四年才颁一次
It's a great thing.
很伟大
It's an amazing honor. Okay everybody that's it for today.
是惊人的荣耀  好吧  下课
Thanks. We'll see you Monday.
谢谢  礼拜一见
We'll be talking about Freud.
下次我们谈佛洛伊德
Why he did enough cocaine to kill a small horse. Thank you.
他为何用古柯碱杀马  谢谢
- How are you?  - It's good to see you.
- 你好吗?  - 真高兴见到你
Good to see you.
很高兴见到你
Sean I think I got something interesting for ya.
我有一件你会感兴趣的事
What you have to have blood and urine? What's up?
干嘛  需要血液和尿液吗?
Why didn't you come to the reunion?
同学会你怎么不来?
You know I'm... I've been busy.
我在忙
You were missed.
大家很想你
Really?
真的?
So how long has it been since we've seen each other?
我们多久没见?
Before Nancy died.
南茜去世前
Yeah I'm sorry.
是  很抱歉
I was in Paris. It was that damn conference.
我在巴黎开会...  都是那该死的会议
I got your card. It was nice.
我收到卡片  很好
- Come here.  - Now that's a takedown.
- 过来  - 投球
Hey.
投得不错
What happened? Did you get leniency or what?
怎么样?  博得同情没?
I got uh probation and then counseling two days a week.
获得保释和一周两次的辅导
Joke. You're a smoothie.
你的伶牙利嘴真不是盖的
Come on Morgan! Just submit!
摩根!  快投球!
Hey Bill just- just get off him. We're gonna miss the game.
放开他  会错过球赛的
I've got a full schedule. I'm very busy.
我行程很满  我很忙
This- This boy is incredible. I've never seen anything like him.
这孩子不可思议  前所未见
What makes him so incredible Gerry?
是什么让他这么不可思议?
You ever heard of Ramanujan?
听过拉玛努强吗?
Yeah yeah. No.
听过...没有
It's a man.
他是个男人
He lived over 100 years ago. He was Indian.
活在一百多年前  印度人
- Dots not feathers.  - Not feathers. Yeah.
- 卓越成就  - 卓越成就
He lived in this tiny hut somewhere in India. He had no formal education.
他住在茅屋里  没受过教育
- He had no access to any scientific work.  - Coffee?
- 无法取得任何科学著述  - 需要咖啡吗?
- You sir?  - Just a little.
- 你呢  先生?  - 一点就好
But he came across this old math book
但他偶然发现一本旧数学课本
and from the simple text he was able to extrapolate theories that had baffled mathematicians for years.
却发明难倒数学家已久的理论
Yes. Continued fractions. He wrote uh...
对  连续分数  他是以...
- Well he mailed it to Hardy at Cambridge.  - Yeah Cambridge. Yeah.
- 他寄给剑桥的哈帝  - 对  剑桥
And Hardy immediately recognized the brilliance of his work.
哈帝即刻了解那是天才之作
And brought him over to England.
把他带到英国
And then they worked together for years.
然后他们合作多年
Creating some of the most exciting math theory ever done.
创造出令人兴奋的数学理论
This- This Ramanujan...his- his genius was unparalleled Sean.
拉玛努强的天才无与伦比
Well this boy's just like that.
这孩子就像他一样
But he's...he's a bit defensive.
但他有点防御性
I need someone who can get through to him.
我需要有人突破他的心防
Like me?
像是我
Yeah like you.
对  就是你
Why?
为什么?
Well because you have the same kind of background.
因为你们有相同背景
What background?
什么背景?
Well you're from the same neighborhood.
你们来自同一个区
He's from Southie?
他是南区人?
Yeah.
是的
Boy genius from Southie.
南区的天才少年
How many shrinks you go to before me?
你之前找过几个心理医生?
Five.
五个
Let me guess. Barry? Henry? Not Rick?
让我猜  拜瑞  亨利  没找瑞克吧
Sean please just meet with him once a week.
拜托  请跟他碰面  一周一次就好
Please?
拜托?
It's a poker game with this kid. Don't let him know what you've got.
这就像打牌  别让牌泄底
He probably even read your book if he could find it.
他或许已看过你的书
It's gonna be hard for him to find.
他要找到很难
Hi Will.
威尔
This is Sean Maguire. Will Hunting.
这是尚恩麦圭尔  威尔杭汀
How are ya?
你好
Yeah. Let's get started.
好  开始
Yeah let's do it.
对  来吧
I'm pumped. Let's let the healing begin.
开始治疗吧
Will you excuse us?
请出去
Yeah please Tom.
对  麻烦你
You too Gerry.
你也出去
Yeah of course.
好  当然
How are you?
你好吗?
Where you from in Southie?
你是南区哪里人?
I like what you've done with the place.
我喜欢你这边的装潢
Oh thanks.
谢谢
Do you buy all these books retail...
这些书都是零买的...
or do you send away for like a "shrink kit" that comes with all these volumes included?
还是派人买的整套心理丛书?
Do you like books?
你喜欢看书?
Yeah.
喜欢
Did you read any of these books?
这些书你读过吗?
I don't know.
不知道
How about any of these books?
那些书呢
Probably not.
大概没有
What about the ones on the top shelf? You read those?
顶层那些呢?  看过没?
Yeah I read those.
看过
Good for you. What do you think about 'em?
很好  你有什么感想?
I'm not here for a fuckin' book report.
我不是他妈的来做读书报告
They're your books. Why don't you read 'em?
那是你的书  你怎么不读
I did. I had to.
我读过  非读不可
Must've taken you a long time.
一定花了你不少时间
Yeah it did.
是的
United States of America: A Complete History Volume l.
美国通史  第一册
Jesus. If you wanna read a real history book
天哪  想看真的历史的话
read Howard Zinn's A People's History in the United States.
应该读辛恩的书
That book'll fuckin' knock you on your ass.
那本书会让你大吃一惊
Better than Chomsky's Manufacturing Consent?
比琼姆斯基的书更好吗?
Do you think that's a good book?
你觉得那是本好书?
You fuckin' people baffle me.
我搞不懂你们这些人  他妈的
You spend all your money on these fuckin' fancy books.
把钱都花在这些可笑的书上
You surround yourselves with 'em. They're the wrong fuckin' books.
浪费在不对的书上面
What are the right fuckin' books Will?
什么是他妈的对的书?
Whatever blows your hair back.
让头发竖起来的
Yeah. Haven't got much hair left.
我剩的头发不多
Hey you know you'd be better shoving that cigarette up your ass.
你为什么不把烟戒了
It'd probably be healthier for you.
对你的健康有好处
Yeah I know. It really gets in the way of my yoga.
我知道  抽烟妨碍我练瑜珈
You work out huh?
你运动吗?
What you lift?
你举重吗?
Yeah.
对
Nautilus?
举重机?
No free weights.
不  哑铃
Oh really?
真的?
Free weights huh?
哑铃?
Yeah. Yeah big time. Just like that.
对  很行
What do you bench?
你举多少?
285. What do you bench?
285  你呢?
You paint that?
你画的?
Yeah. Do you paint?
对  你画画吗?
Do you sculpt?
你雕塑吗?
No.
不
Do you like art?
喜欢艺术吗?
No.
不
Do you like music?
喜欢音乐吗?
This is a real piece of shit.
真烂
Oh tell me what you really think.
告诉我你觉得怎么样
Just the linear and impressionistic mix makes a very muddled composition.
线条结构复杂混乱
It's also a Winslow Homer rip- off except you got whitey rowin' the boat there.
笔法颇有印象派画风
Well it's art Monet. It wasn't very good.
那倒怪了  我并不想模仿莫奈
That's not really what concerns me though.
我在意的不是那个
What concerns you?
你在意什么?
Just the coloring.
色彩
You know what the real bitch of it is?
你知道吗?
It's paint- by- number.
这是以数字画的
Is it color- by- number? Because the colors are fascinating to me.
以数字上色?  至少这色彩让我着迷
Aren't they really?
真的?  色彩怎样?
You bet. I think you're about one step away from cuttin' your fuckin' ear off.
我想你差点就要割耳朵了
Really?
真的?
Oh yeah.
没错
Think I should move to the south of France change my name to "Vincent".
那我应该搬到法国改名梵谷
You ever heard the sayin' "any port in a storm"?
听过"暴风雨中的港口"吗?
Yeah.
听过
Yeah maybe that means you.
也许指的就是你
In what way?
哪方面?
Maybe you're in the middle of a storm a big fuckin' storm.
也许你正在暴风雨中
Yeah maybe.
也许吧
The sky's fallin' on your head. The waves are crashin' over your little boat.
天色昏暗  海浪撞击小船
The oars are about to snap.
桨就要断了
You just piss in your pants. You're cryin' for the harbor.
你吓坏了  迫切需要港口
So maybe you do what you gotta do to get out. You know maybe you became a psychologist.
这是你成为心理医生的原因
Bingo. That's it.
答对了  就是这样
Let me do my job now. You start with me. Come on.
让我做事吧  你妨碍我了
Maybe you married the wrong woman.
也许你娶错女人
Maybe you should watch your mouth.
也许你讲话该小心点
Watch it right there chief all right?
小心点  好吗?
That's it isn't it? You married the wrong woman.
没错  你娶错女人了
What happened?
发生什么事?
What did she leave you?
她抛弃你了?
Was she you know...banging some other guy?
她是不是搞上别的男人?
If you ever disrespect my wife again I will end you.
再对我太太无礼就宰了你
I will fuckin' end you.
我会他妈的宰了你
Got that chief?
听到没?
Time's up.
时间到了
Yeah.
是的
At ease gentlemen.
稍息  两位
You okay?
你没事吧?
Look I'll understand if you don't wanna meet with him again.
如果你不再想见他  我了解
Thursday 4:00.
星期四下午四点
Make sure the kid's here.
一定要他来
Yeah. Thanks.
好  谢谢
Well you look lovely in those glasses.
你戴那副眼镜好可爱
Thank you very much.
多谢你
They're just beautiful.
真漂亮
Yes I always wanted dark blue eye shadow.
我一直想擦蓝色眼影
Wonderful.
美极了
Growing up in England you know I went to a very nice school.
我在英国长大  念好学校
You know it was kind of progressive organic...
就是那种积极  有组织...
do- it- yourself private school.
又独立自主的私立学校
Then Harvard. Hopefully med school.
然后是很有钱途的哈佛医学院
You know I figured out
你知道我发现什么?
by the end my brain's gonna be worth $250  000.
最后我的脑子  会价值25万美金
That sounded horrible didn't it?
听起来很可怕吧
Bring me another mai tai!
再来一杯"迈泰"
Yeah that's cool. I mean I bet your parents were happy to pay.
酷  你父母一定很乐于付钱
No I was happy to pay. I inherited the money.
错  我自己付  我继承了遗产
Wow. Is Harvard gettin' all that money?
那么钱都给哈佛吗?
No Stanford. I'm going there in June when I graduate.
不  斯坦福  毕业后过去
All right so you just wanted to use this sailor and then run away huh?
所以你只是想利用这个水手
I was gonna you know experiment on you for anatomy class first obviously.
我要先拿你做解剖实验
In that case that's fine.
这样的话  好吧
Hey you wanna see my magic tricks Skylar?
想看我变魔术吗?
Of course.
好啊
All right. Promise to...
好  保证...
All right.
好的
This one's for you Rudolph.
这是给你的  鲁道夫
Wait wait. You need my wand.
等等  你需要我的魔杖
All right give me a hit. Thank you. All right.
好  敲一下
I'm gonna make all these caramels disappear.
谢谢  让这些焦糖消失
You ready? Ready.
准备好了吗?
One two three.
一 二 三
They're all gone.
全不见了
That was my...It works better when I have my rabbit.
有兔子会比较成功
I don't really date you know that much.
我不常约会
How very unfortunate... I think for me.
真可惜  我...
You know what I mean? I know you've been thinking about it.
你懂我意思  我知道你在想什么
- Oh no I haven't.  - Yes you have.
- 我没有  - 我知道你有
No I really haven't.
真的没有
Yes you have. You were hoping to get a good night kiss.
你有  你想要睡前一吻
No you know I tell ya I was hopin' to get a good night laid.
不  我想要睡前一炮
But I'll settle for like a kiss you know?
我愿意勉强接受一吻
How very noble of you.
你很高尚
Thank you.
谢谢
No I was...I was hopin' for a kiss.
不  我真的想要一吻
Well why don't we just get it out of the way now?
何不现在就解决?
Right now?
现在?
Yeah. Come on.
对  来
I think I got some of your pickle.
我吃到你的酸黄瓜了
You again huh?
又是你?
Come with me.
跟我来
So what's this?
现在要干嘛?
A Taster's Choice moment between guys?
这是男人的行家选择?
This is really nice.
这里真不错
You got a thing for swans? Is this like a fetish?
你喜欢天鹅?  这算恋物癖吗?
Is it something like maybe we need to devote some time to?
这是需要花点时间的事吗?
Thought about what you said to me the other day. About my painting.
我在想你批评我画的事
Stayed up half the night thinking about it.
失眠大半夜的思索后
Something occurred to me.
突然我想到一件事
I fell into a deep peaceful sleep and haven't thought about you since.
接着就沉沉入睡
You know what occurred to me?
你知道我当时想到什么吗?
No.
不知道
You're just a kid.
你只是个孩子
You don't have the faintest idea what you're talking about.
你根本不晓得你在说什么
Why thank you.
谢谢  为什么?
It's all right.
没关系
You've never been out of Boston.
因你没离开过波士顿
Nope.
是没有
So if I asked you about art you'd probably give me the skinny...
所以问你艺术  你可能会...
on every art book ever written.
提出艺术书籍中的粗浅论调
Michelangelo? You know a lot about him.
有关米开朗基罗  你知道很多
Life's work political aspirations. Him and the pope...
他的政治抱负  他和教皇...
Sexual orientation. The whole works right?
性倾向  所有作品  对吗?
I bet you can't tell me what it smells like in the Sistine Chapel.
但你不知道西斯汀教堂的气味
You never actually stood there and looked up at that beautiful ceiling.
你从没站在那儿观赏美丽的天花板
Seeing that.
我看过
If I ask you about women.
如果我问关于女人的事
you'll probably give me a syllabus of your personal favorites.
你八成会说出个人偏好的谬论
You may have even been laid a few times.
你可能上过几次床
But you can't tell me what it feels like to wake up next to a woman...
但你说不出在女人身旁醒来...
and feel truly happy.
那种幸福的滋味
You're a tough kid.
你是个很倔的孩子
I ask you about war you'd probably throw Shakespeare at me right?
问战争  你会说莎士比亚的话
"Once more into the breach dear friends."
"共赴战场  亲爱的朋友"
But you've never been near one.
但你从没接近过战争
You've never held your best friend's head in your lap...
从没把好友的头抱在膝盖上...
and watch him gasp his last breath lookin' to you for help.
看着他吐出最后一口气
If I asked you about love you'd probably quote me a sonnet.
问爱情  你会引述十四行诗
But you've never looked at a woman and been totally vulnerable.
但你从没看过女人的脆弱
Known someone that could level you with her eyes.
她能以双眼击倒你
Feelin' like God put an angel on Earth just for you.
感觉上帝让天使为你下凡
Who could rescue you from the depths of hell.
她能从地狱将你拯救出来
And you wouldn't know what it's like to be her angel.
你不了解成为她天使的滋味
To have that love for her be there forever.
拥有对她的爱直到永远
Through anything. Through cancer.
经历这一切  经历癌症
And you wouldn't know about sleepin' sittin' up in a hospital room for two months holding her hand.
你无法体会在医院睡整整两个月  握着她的手
because the doctors could see in your eyes...
因为医生看到你的眼神就明白...
that the terms "visiting hours" don't apply to you.
会客时间的规定对你无效
You don't know about real loss
你不了解真正的失去
'cause that only occurs when you love something more than you love yourself.
唯有爱别人胜于自己才能体会
I doubt you've ever dared to love anybody that much.
我怀疑你敢那样爱人
I look at you. I don't see an intelligent confident man.
看着你  我没看到聪明自信
I see a cocky scared shitless kid.
我看到被吓傻的狂妄孩子
But you're a genius Will. No one denies that.
但你是天才  没人能否认
No one could possibly understand the depths of you.
没人能了解你的深度
But you presume to know everything about me because you saw a painting of mine.
但你看我的画就认定了解我
You ripped my fuckin' life apart.
你把我的人生撕裂了
You're an orphan right?
你是孤儿  对吧?
Do you think I'd know the first thing about how hard your life has been...
你想我觉得你日子有多苦...
how you feel who you are...
你的感受  你是谁...
because I read Oliver Twist?
只是因为我看过孤雏泪吗?
Does that encapsulate you?
太轻易认定你了吗?
Personally I don't give a shit about all that because...
我不在乎  因为...
You know what? I can't learn anything from you...I can't read in some fuckin' book.
你知道吗?  我不能靠任何书籍认识你
Unless you wanna talk about you who you are.
除非你想谈自己  谈你是谁
And I'm fascinated. I'm in.
那我就有兴趣了  我愿意加入
But you don't wanna do that do you sport?
但你不想那么做  对吗?
You're terrified of what you might say.
你怕你会被说出来的话吓到
Your move chief.
轮到你说了  大哥
Hello? Hello?
喂?
Hello?
Professor Valenti are you calling me again?
瓦兰帝教授  又是你吗?
Freak.
怪胎
Christ who did you call?
天哪  你打给谁?
No one. I forgot the number.
没有  我忘了号码
You fuckin' retarded?
你他妈智障?
You went all the way out there in the rain and you didn't bring the number.
冒雨打电话  竟忘了号码
No it was your mother's 900 number. I just ran out of quarters.
那是你妈的免费电话
Why don't we get off on mothers? I just got off yours.
别扯上我妈  我刚上过你妈
That's pretty funny Morgan. That's a fuckin' nickel bitch.
很好笑  摩根  太炫了
- Keep antagonizing me. Watch what happens.- All right then Morgan.
- 继续跟我作对看看  - 好了
- Watch what happens.- All right then Morgan.
- 等着瞧  - 好了  摩根
Keep fuckin' with me.
再整我啊
No smoking.
不准抽烟
What do you mean he didn't talk? You were in there for an hour.
什么叫没讲话?  一个钟头
He just sat there counting the seconds until the session was over.
他就坐着等会谈结束
Pretty impressive actually.
让人印象蛮深刻的
Why would he do that?
他为什么要那么做?
To prove to me he doesn't have to talk to me if he doesn't want to.
证明他不想讲就不必讲
What is this? Some kind of staring contest between two kids from the old neighborhood?
这是小孩玩的瞪人比赛吗?
Yeah it is and I can't talk first.
对  而且我不能先讲话
We know your theory Alexander.
我们知道你的理论  亚历山大
But the boy's found a simple geometrical picture.
但这孩子找出简单的几何图
A tree structure won't work.
树状结构行不通
Look now. He's joining the two vertices.
他把两个顶点连起来了
But I can do the sum.
但我算出总数
It's how you group the terms Alexander.
那是集合项的方法
But Gerry. If we do the whole thing this way then...
但是如果这样做...
Hey look look.
看这里
I wrote it down. It's simpler this way.
我写下来了  这样比较简单
Sometimes people get lucky.
有些人就是走运
You're a brilliant man.
你是很聪明的人
You know I was on this plane once and I'm sittin' there and...
我有一次搭飞机  坐在机上...
the captain gets on he does his whole you know "we'll be cruisin' at 35000 feet  "
机长广播完飞行于三万五千尺
But then he puts the mike down. He forgets to turn it off.
他放下麦克风后忘了关掉
So he turns to the copilot. He's like...
他转向副驾驶说...
"You know all I could use right now is a fuckin' blow job and a cup of coffee."
我现在很想要口交和咖啡
So the stewardess fuckin' goes bombin' up from the back of the plane to tell him the microphone's still on.
空服员冲去跟他说麦克风没关
This guy in the back of the plane's like "Hey hon don't forget the coffee."
机尾有个人说"别忘了带上咖啡"
You ever been on a plane?
你搭过飞机?
No but it's a fuckin' joke.
没有  那只是个笑话
It works better if I tell it in the first person.
用第一人称比较好笑
Yeah it does.
没错
I have been laid you know?
我做过爱
Really? Good for you.
真的?  很好
Big time big time.
我很厉害
Big time huh?
很厉害?
I went on a date last week.
对  我上礼拜有约会
How'd it go?
怎么样?
It was good.
很好
Goin' out again?
要再约会吗?
I don't know.
不知道
Why not?
为什么?
Haven't called her.
我没打给她
Christ you're an amateur.
天哪  你真没用
- I know what I'm doin'.  - Really?
- 我知道我在干嘛  - 真的吗?
Yeah. Don't worry about me. I know what I'm doin'.
放心  我知道我在干嘛
Yeah but this girl was like you know beautiful. She's smart. She's fun.
这女孩很漂亮  聪明风趣
She's different from most of the girls I've been with.
她跟我以前认识的女生不一样
So call her up Romeo.
那就打给她  罗密欧
Why so I can realize she's not that smart.
让自己发现她没那么聪明吗?
That she's fuckin' boring? You know I mean you don't...
发现她其实很无聊吗?
This girl's like fuckin' perfect right now.
这女孩现在很完美
I don't wanna ruin that.
我不想破坏
Maybe you're perfect right now. Maybe you don't wanna ruin that.
或许是你不想破坏你自己的完美
But I think that's a super philosophy Will.
我觉得那是极好的哲学
That way you can go through your entire life without ever having to really know anybody.
这样可以一辈子不认识任何人
My wife used to fart when she was nervous.
我太太一紧张就放屁
She had all sorts of wonderful idiosyncrasies.
她有各种奇妙的小特质
You know she used to fart in her sleep.
你知道  她睡觉会放屁
Just thought I'd share that with you.
抱歉跟你讲这种事
One night it was so loud it woke the dog up.
有天晚上大声到把狗吵醒
She woke up and gone like "Was that you?" I said "Yeah."
她醒来说  是你吗  我说是
I didn't have the heart to tell her. Oh God.
我不忍心告诉她  天哪
She woke herself up?
她把自己臭醒?
Yes.
是的
Oh Christ. But Will she's been dead two years
天哪  她去世两年了
And that's the shit I remember.
而那是我记得的事
It's wonderful stuff you know? Little things like that.
像那样的小事很奇妙
Yeah but those are the things I miss the most.
那是我最想念的事
Those little idiosyncrasies that only I knew about. That's what made her my wife.
这些小特质让她成为我太太
Boy and she had the goods on me too. She knew all my little peccadillos.
她也知道我所有的小瑕疵
People call these things "imperfections".
人们称之为不完美
But they're not. That's the good stuff.
其实不然  那才是好东西
And then we get to choose who we let into our weird little worlds.
能选择让谁进入我们的世界
You're not perfect sport.
你并不完美
And let me save you the suspense.
我不吊你胃口
This girl you met she isn't perfect either.
你认识的女生也不完美
But the question is whether or not you're perfect for each other.
问题是你们是否完美地合适
That's the whole deal. That's what intimacy is all about.
亲密关系就是这么回事
Now you can know everything in the world sport.
你可以知道全世界的事
but the only way you're findin' out that one is by givin' it a shot.
但发掘的方法就是去尝试
You certainly won't learn from an old fucker like me.
你不能跟我这个糟老头学
Even if I did know I wouldn't tell a pissant like you.
就算我知道我也不告诉你
Yeah why not?
为什么?
You told me every other fuckin' thing. Jesus Christ.
你其他事都告诉我了  天哪
Fuckin' talk more than any shrink I ever seen in my life.
你的话比任何心理医生都多
I teach the shit. I didn't say I knew how to do it.
我只是教心理学  我说过我不是心理医生
You ever think about gettin' remarried?
那么  你想过再婚吗?
My wife's dead.
我太太死了
Hence the word "remarried."
所以才叫"再婚"
She's dead.
她死了
Yeah well I think that's a super philosophy Sean.
我想那是极好的哲学
I mean that way you can actually go through the rest of your life without ever really knowing anybody.
这样可以一辈子不认识任何人
Time's up.
时间到了
Hold it open.
别关
Thanks.
谢谢
Where have you been?
你去哪里了?
I'm sorry. I've been like...I've been really busy and...
对不起  我...我很忙
Mmm. Me too.
我也是
Yeah. I...I thought you'd call.
我以为你会打来
I mean.
我是说
- We had a really good time.  - I had a really good time too.
- 我们相处愉快  - 的确如此
I mean I just...I...I'm sorry you know. I blew it.
对不起我搞砸了
No. No I mean you know it's all right.
不  没关系
Yeah um so I was wonderin' if uh if you know you'd give me another crack at it.
你会不会再让我试一遍
You know let me take you out again.
让我再约你出去
I can't.
不行
All right.
好吧
Oh no I didn't...I didn't mean I can't like ever.
不  我不是永远不行
I just can't right now.
现在不行
I've got to assign the proton spectrum for "ebogamine".
我得做质子光谱分配
All that sounds really really interesting. It's actually fantastically boring.
听起来有趣  其实很无聊
- All right um...  - Maybe some other time.
- 好吧  - 或许改天吧
Like tomorrow?
那明天呢?
Um yeah all right.
好啊
- Okay.  - Okay.
- 好的  - 好的
- Bye.  - Bye.
- 再见  - 再见
What are you doing here?
你在这儿干嘛?
I couldn't wait till tomorrow.
我等不到明天了
Where the fuck did you get this?
你从哪儿弄到这个?
I had to sleep with someone in your class.
我得跟你同学上床
Oh I hope it was someone with the open- toed sandals and the really bad breath.
希望是个穿拖鞋又有口臭的人
Come on. Let's go have some fun.
走  去找乐子
No I've got to learn this.
不行  我得念这个
Well you're not going into surgery tomorrow are you?
你不会明天就要开刀吧
No.
不是
Let's go.
走吧
Oh my God! My dog is winning!
我的天  我的狗赢了
Come on Misty! Come on! Run! Look at that! Come on!
加油  迷雾!  快跑!
Look there he goes. Misty run! Come on!
他在那边  迷雾领先!
We won.
我们赢了
He totally won.
它大获全胜
So did you grow up around here then?
你在这边长大的吗?
Not far. South Boston.
不远  南波士顿
Still glowing from my win.
赢了比赛让我脸好热
Look at you. You're so happy.
看你乐成这样
And what was that like then?
我的样子还好吧
It was normal I guess. Nothin' special.
很正常  没什么特别
Do you got lots of brothers and sisters?
你有很多兄弟姊妹吗?
- Do I have a lot of brothers and sisters?  - That's what I said.
- 我有很多兄弟姊妹吗?  - 我在问你呢
Well Irish Catholic what do you think?
我是个天主教徒  你说呢?
Right. That's right. How many?
对  几个?
You wouldn't believe me if I told you.
告诉你你也不信
Why? Go on. What? Five?
为什么?  说啊  五个?
Seven? Eight? How many?
七个?  八个?  几个?
I have 12 big brothers.
我有十二个哥哥
You do not!
你才没有!
No I swear to God. I swear to God. I'm lucky 13 right here.
我发誓  我是幸运十三
Do you know all their names?
你知道他们的名字吗?
Do I...Yeah they're my brothers.
当然知道  他们是我哥哥
What are they called?
叫什么名字?
Marky Ricky Danny Terry...
马奇  瑞奇  丹尼  泰瑞...
Mikey Davey Timmy Tommy...
麦奇  大卫  提米  汤米...
Joey Robby Johnny and Brian.
乔依  罗比  强尼和布莱恩
Say it again.
再说一遍
Marky Ricky Danny Terry...
马奇  瑞奇  丹尼  泰瑞...
Mikey Davey Timmy Tommy...
麦奇  大卫  提米  汤米...
Joey Robby Johnny and Brian.
乔依  罗比  强尼和布莱恩
And Willy.
还有小威
Willy?
小威?
Will.
威尔
Do you still see all of them?
你常和他们见面吗?
Yeah well they all live in Southie.
他们都住南区
I'm livin' with three of 'em right now.
我跟其中三个住
Oh yeah?
是吗?
I'd like to meet them.
我好想见他们
Yeah we'll do that.
好  就去见他们
Oh you know I read your book last night.
我昨晚读过你的书
Oh so you're the one.
原来是你
Do you still uh...Do you still counsel veterans?
你还辅导退伍军人吗?
No I don't.
没有
Why not?
为什么?
Well I gave it up when my wife got sick.
我太太生病时就没做了
You ever wonder what your life would be like if you
你有没有想过若没遇见你太太
uh if you never met your wife?
你的生活会怎样?
What? Wonder if I'd be better off without her?
没有她会不会比较好?
No no no I'm not saying like better off.
不  我没说比较好
I didn't mean it like that.
我没那意思
It's all right. It's an important question.
没关系  很重要的问题
'Cause you'll have bad times...
是会有不好的时候...
But that'll always wake you up to the good stuff you weren't paying attention to.
但那总是让你觉悟到好的事
And you don't regret meetin' your wife?
你不后悔认识你太太?
Why? 'Cause the pain I feel now?
因为我现在的痛苦?
Oh I got regrets Will.
是有遗憾
But I don't regret a single day I spent with her.
但我不后悔跟她共度的每一天
So when did you know like that she was the one for you?
你几时知道她是理想对象?
October 21 1975.
1975年10月21日
Jesus Christ. You know the fuckin' day?
天哪  你他妈的记得日期?
Oh yeah 'cause it was game six of the World Series.
对  那是世界大赛第六场
Biggest game in Red Sox history.
红袜队史上最重大的球赛
Yeah sure.
没错
My friends and I had slept out all night to get tickets.
我和朋友睡人行道排队买票
You got tickets?
你有票?
Yep. Day of the game...
对  比赛当天...
I was sittin' in a bar waitin' for the game to start...
我们坐在酒吧等球赛开始...
and in walks this girl...
有个女孩走进来...
It was an amazing game though.
那是场很棒的球赛
You know bottom of the eighth Carbo ties it up.
八局下半
It was 6- 6.
六比六平手
It went to 12. Bottom of the 12th.
打到第十二局  下半场时
in stepped Carlton Fisk old Pudge.
矮冬瓜菲克斯上场
Steps up to the plate. You know he's got that weird stance.
他站上本垒  姿势很怪
And then...Boom! He clocks it you know.
打击出去!
High fly ball down the left field line!
左外野高飞球!
Thirty- five thousand people on their feet yellin' at the ball.
三万五千人站起来对球吼
But that's nothin' 'cause Fisk he's wavin' at the ball like a madman.
菲斯克像发了疯似地挥手说
"Get over! Get over! Get over!"
"飞过去!  飞过去!  飞过去!"
Then it hits the foul pole. He goes ape- shit.
然后球飞到边界
And 35  000 fans...They charge the field you know.
三万五千名球迷冲到场上
Yeah and he's fuckin' blowin' people outta the way. "Get outta the way! Get outta the way!"
他大叫"大家让开  让开..."
I can't fuckin' believe you had tickets to that fuckin' game!
我真不敢相信你有票!
Did you rush the field?
你有冲到场上吗?
No I didn't rush the fuckin' field. I wasn't there.
我没冲到场上  我不在场
What?
什么?
No I was in a bar havin' a drink with my future wife.
我跟我未来的老婆在喝酒
You missed Pudge Fisk's home run.
你错过菲斯克的全垒打?
Right.
对
to have a fuckin' drink with some lady you never met?
跟一个不认识的女人喝酒?
Yeah but you should have seen her. She was a stunner.
对  你该看看她  令人惊艳
I don't care if...
我才不管他妈的...
Oh no no she lit up the room.
她让整个屋子亮起来
- I don't care if Helen of Troy walks into the room.  - Oh Helen of Troy!
- 哪怕是走进来的是海伦我也不在乎  - 你疯了!
That's game six! Oh my God and who were these friends of yours?
天哪  那你朋友呢
- They let you get away with that?  - They had to.
- 就这么放过你?  - 他们没办法
What did you say to 'em?
你跟他们怎么说?
I just slid my ticket across the table.
我把票滑过去说
I said "Sorry guys. I gotta see about a girl."
抱歉  我要去找一个女孩
- "I gotta go see about a girl"?  - Yes!
- 我要去找一个女孩?  - 对!
That's what you said?
你那么说?
They let you get away with that?
他们就放过你了?
Oh yeah. They saw it in my eyes that I meant it.
对  他们看到我认真的眼睛
You're kiddin' me?
你耍我吧
No I'm not kidding you Will.
我没耍你
That's why I'm not talkin' right now about some girl I saw at a bar 20 years ago...
所以我现在不会因为...
and how I always regretted not goin' over and talkin' to her.
当年没和她说话而懊悔终生
I don't regret the 18 years I was married to Nancy.
我不后悔跟南茜结的18年
I don't regret the six years I had to give up counseling when she got sick.
不后悔为她的病放弃辅导
And I don't regret the last years when she got really sick.
不后悔那最后几年守着重病的她
And I sure as hell don't regret missin' a damn game.
更不会后悔错过球赛
That's regret.
只是有点遗憾
Would have been nice to catch that game though.
看到那场球赛还是不错的
I didn't know Pudge was gonna hit a home run.
我不晓得矮冬瓜会红不让
You know I'm very very useful on the court. I'm extremely tall.
我在球场上很有用  我很高
You're not that tall.
你没那么高
I dunk.
我会灌篮
Will I ever play in the N.B.A.?
我能打NBA吗?
"It is decidedly so." Hmph.
绝对可以
Why do we always stay here?
为什么老是待在这边?
'Cause it's nicer than my place.
因为比我家好
Yes but I've never seen your place.
但我从没去过你家
I know.
我知道
When am I gonna meet your friends and your brothers?
我什么时候能见到你朋友和哥哥?
Well they don't really come down here that much.
他们不常来这里
I think I can make it to South Boston.
我可以到南波士顿
It's kind of a hike.
有点远
Is it me you're hiding from them or the other way around?
是我还是他们见不得人?
All right we'll go.
好  我们去
When?
几时?
I don't know. We'll go sometime next week.
不知道  下礼拜吧
What if I said I would not sleep with you again until you let me meet your friends?
如不让我见他们就再也不跟你上床
I'd say it's like 4:30 in the mornin'. They're probably up.
清晨四点半  他们应该醒了
Oh my God. Men are shameless.
天哪  男人真无耻
If you're not thinking with your wiener then you're acting directly on its behalf.
你们男人就只会用小弟弟思考
You bet. And on behalf of my wiener can I get an advance payment?
仅代表我的小弟弟向你预支
I don't know. Let's ask.
不知道  我问问
"Outlook does not look good."
前途无量
- What?  - Fuck the...
- 什么?  - 干
Hey Chuck. No. Nothing. Go back to sleep.
查克  没事  继续睡
"Outlook"? That's the same thing that told you you was gonna play in the N.B.A.
你去打NBA才前途无量
Exactly so look out. You'd better start buying some season tickets.
没错  所以你最好开始买季票
Mmm! I plan to. I'm tall. I like wearing shorts.
我很高  我喜欢穿短裤
Hook hook. Dunk dunk.
勾射  灌篮
You're not that tall.
你没那么高
Yes I am. Maybe I'm all about three points.
我有  我三分射篮很行
I'm all about home runs.
我就很会打"全垒打"
Stop mixing your sporting metaphors.
别用运动术语影射
A leprechaun's got his dick in the monkey's ass.
妖精的老二在猴子屁眼里
Morgan comes runnin' in goin' "l don't mind it. I don't mind..."
摩根跑出来说  我不介意  我不介意
Well I can't believe you brought Skylar here when we're fuckin' all bombed and drinkin'.
干  你竟挑我们烂醉时带她来
I know Morgan. It's a real rarity we'd be all drinkin'.
我们很难得一起喝酒
My uncle Marty drinks. He'll go on a bender for six eight months.
我叔叔马帝只要一喝酒  就会狂欢个一年半载
Did I ever tell ya what happened to him when he was drivin' up there and got pulled over?
我讲过他被拦下来的事没?
I told you guys right? Let me tell ya what happened to my uncle Marty.
我跟你们讲
Because you oughta know this.
你们应该知道
He's always tellin' stories. Every time we come here he's got another story.
到这边老是听他讲故事
But we all heard this one.
这个我们早就听过了
Go ahead. Say it anyway.
还是说吧  快讲
I will go ahead. Thanks a lot. Guess I have the floor now.
我会讲  多谢  换我发言
My uncle Marty's drivin' home right?
我叔叔开车回家
Bombed out of his tree right?
撞到树上
Just hammered out of his gourd. Just wrecked.
他醉得一塌糊涂
This state trooper sees him pulls him over. So my uncle's fucked basically.
州警把他拦下来  我叔叔惨了
Got him out of the car tryin' to make him walk the line.
州警要他下车走直线
He gets out of the car pukes...
结果他吐在州警身上...
and the statie's pretty sure he's over the legal limit.
州警确信他超过酒精浓度
So he's about to throw the cuffs on him and put him in jail.
正要把他戴上手铐送去坐牢
All of a sudden 50 yards down the road there's this huge fuckin' boom.
突然五十码外一声他妈的巨响
Statie gets real spooked. He turns around.
州警吓一大跳  转身
He got shot?
枪声?
No. So...So...
不  是...
You heard this story before.
你听过这故事了
Yeah Morgan stop. Stop.
得了  摩根
Some other guy's car had hit a tree. There was an accident.
是别人的车撞到树  出事了
Anyway...
总之...
Shut the fuck up!
闭嘴!
I'm gonna break your neck.
我要扭断你脖子
Shut up!
闭嘴
He told you the story once before.
他跟你说过这故事了
So he tells my uncle "Stay here. Don't move."
州警跟我叔叔说"别走"
Statie goes runnin' down the road to deal with the other accident.
就跑去处理另一起事故
After a few minutes of just lyin' in his own piss and vomit...
躺在尿和呕吐物中几分钟后...
my uncle starts wonderin' what he's doin' there.
我叔叔才想到  他在那儿干嘛
Gets up gets in his car and just drives home.
于是站起来开车回家
The next mornin' my uncle's just passed out.
隔天早上我叔叔还昏迷不醒
He hears this knockin' at the door.
他听到敲门声
So he goes downstairs pulls the door open "What?"
下楼拉开门说"什么事"
It's the state trooper that pulled him over.
是拦下他的州警
Statie says "Fuck you mean 'What?' You know what."
州警说"我操  什么事?  你明知故问"
"I pulled you over last night is what and you took off."
"我昨晚拦下你  你逃走了"
He's like "l never seen you before in my life.
叔叔说"我这辈子没见过你"
I've been home all night with my kids. I don't know who the fuck you are."
"我整晚在家  你乱讲什么"
He's like "You know who I am. Let me get in your garage."
州警说"别装蒜了  到车库"
My uncle's like "What?" He said
我叔叔说"什么?"
"You heard me. Let me get in your garage."
州警说"带我去你的车库"
He was like "All right. Fine." Takes him out to the garage opens the door.
我叔叔带他到车库打开门
And there's...The statie's police cruiser is in my uncle's garage.
警车就在我叔叔的车库里
He was so fuckin'...He was so fuckin' hammered he drove the wrong car home.
他醉到他妈的开错车回家了
The best part about it is the fuckin' state trooper...
最诺氖侵菥好糗...
was so embarrassed he didn't do anything.
他整晚什么都没做
He'd been drivin' around all night in my uncle's Chevelle lookin' for the house.
开着我叔叔的车挨家挨户找人
All right Chuck what the fuck is the point of your story?
你的故事重点是什么?
He got away. That's the point.
他逃跑了就是重点
- Well question...  - Come on.
- 好  问题是...  - 你是不是...
Stop.
少来了
- I'm tryin' to clarify somethin'.  - You're embarrassing him.
- 你想弄清楚又不好意思问  - 好了  你别糗人家了
- It doesn't make any sense.  - It does make sense.
- 因为你讲的故事没什么意义  - 没什么意义
if you listen to the story and quit askin' questions.
听故事别问东问西的
Well let's see if you can get this one. I've got a little story for you.
摩根  看这个故事你懂不懂
All right there's an old couple in bed.
好  一对老夫妻在床上
Mary and Paddie.
玛丽和派帝
They wake up on the morning of their 50th anniversary.
结婚50周年那天他们醒来
Mary looks over and gazes adoringly at Paddie.
玛丽深情地望着派帝说
She's like "Oh Jesus Paddie. You're such a good- looking feller. I love ya.
天哪  你真是一个大帅哥  我爱你
I want to give ya a little present.
我要送你一件礼物
Anything your little heart desires I'm goin' to give it to ya.
你渴望什么我都给你
What would ya like?
你想要什么?
Paddie's like "Oh gee Mary. That's a very sweet offer.
派帝说这真是甜蜜的提议
Now in 50 years there's one thing that's been missing.
五十年来就少一样东西
and uh I would like you to give me a blow job. I would like for it."
我希望你帮我吹喇叭  我想要
Mary's like "All right."
玛丽说好
She takes her teeth out...
她把假牙拿掉...
puts 'em in the glass. She gives him a blow job.
放进杯子里  然后帮他吹
Afterwards Paddie's like "Yeah geez now that's what I've been missin'.
之后派帝说  这就是我最渴望
That was the most beautiful earth- shattering thing ever!
最勾魂摄魄的事  他说
Beautiful Mary! I love ya!
太棒了  玛丽  我爱你
Is there anything that I can do for you?"
我能为你做什么吗?
Mary looks up to him and she goes "Give us a kiss."
玛丽抬头看他说  "亲一下"
Oh my God!
我的天
That's filthy.
好恶
It's not that filthy. I've heard filthy.
不恶  我听过更恶心的
Get off of me!
滚开  操!
All right. See you guys later.
好  再见
All right. Take it easy Bill.
保重  比利
So Skylar thanks for comin' by. Changed my opinion of Harvard people.
谢谢你改变我对哈佛人的看法
You don't want to rush to judgment on that one 'cause they're not all like me.
别急着下断语  他们跟我不同
Oh. I'm sure. It was nice to meet ya.
我相信  很高兴认识你
Take it easy. Slowly back away.
小心
Oh come on. Brother.
慢慢让开
I don't know what you're doin' dude. You're givin' us a ride.
你在干嘛?  你要送我们
What the fuck do I look like to you?
你以为我在干嘛?
You're walkin' bitch. Will's takin' the car.
你要走路  车给威尔
All right thanks sucker. I appreciate it.
好  谢了  很感激
I don't know what you're gettin' all serious about.
干嘛这么正经
You're droppin' me off first.
你还是要先送我回家
It's really out of the way.
这样很不顺路
Oh okay. Just 'cause you don't have to sleep in your one- room palace tonight...
别以为今晚可以外宿...
don't start thinkin' you're bad.
就懦烧庋
Hey wait a minute. You said we were gonna see your place.
等一下  你说要去看你家
Not tonight.
今晚不行
Oh no not tonight. Not any other night.
今晚不行  哪一晚都不行
He knows once you see that shit- hole he's gettin' dropped like a bad habit.
他知道你一看过就会甩了他
But I wanted to meet your brothers.
但我想见你哥哥
We're gonna do that another time.
不  改天吧
All right.
好吧
Need them keys.
我需要钥匙
The stewardess hears this and goes haulin' ass down the aisle.
空服员听到就往走道上冲
I yell "Don't forget the coffee."
我说"别忘了咖啡"
No shit! You didn't say that.
狗屁!  你没那么说
For Christ's sake Marty it's a joke.
拜托  那是笑话嘛
I know someone that actually happened to Marty.
我认识真的碰到这事的人
A joke.
只是个笑话
Gerry.
杰洛
Have trouble findin' the place?
这边很难找吗?
No I took a cab.
不会  我搭计程车
Timmy this is Gerry. We went to college together.
提米  这是杰洛  大学同学
How you doin'? Nice to meet ya.
你好  幸会
Pleased to meet you.
幸会
Can I get you a beer?
请你喝杯啤酒吧
Um no just a Perrier.
不  沛绿雅
That's French for club soda.
那是法文的苏打水
Club soda yeah.
苏打水  好
Couple of sandwiches too.
还有几个三明治
Sure.
好
Put it on my tab.
算在我帐上
You ever plannin' on payin' your tab?
你打算要签帐吗?
Yeah chief got the winning lottery ticket right here.
要  我这边有中奖彩券
What's the jackpot?
奖金多少?
Twelve million.
一千两百万
I don't think that'll cover it.
我看不够付
It'll cover your sex change operation.
够付你的变性手术了
Nuts?
坚果?
No thank you.
不  谢谢
So you wanted to talk about Will.
你想谈威尔
Well it seems to be going well.
好像很顺利
I think so.
我想是的
Have you talked to him at all about his future?
你跟他谈过未来没?
No we haven't gotten into that yet. We're still bangin' away at the past.
没谈到  还在往事中打转
Maybe you should.
该开始谈了
My phone's been ringing off the hook with job offers.
许多工作都急着找他
What kind?
哪种工作?
Cutting edge mathematics think tanks.
尖端科技数学  智囊团
The kind of place where a mind like Will's is given free rein.
威尔的头脑能发挥的地方
That's great that there are offers but I don't really think he's ready for that.
那真好  但他还没准备好
I'm not sure you understand Sean.
我想你不明白
What don't I understand?
我不明白什么?
Here you go guys.
来了
Thanks Tim.
谢谢你
Just so you don't get sticky fingers.
这样手指不会拧拧的
Tim can you help us?
提米  能帮个忙吗?
We're tryin' to settle a bet.
我们要赌一赌输赢
Ever heard of Jonas Salk?
听过乔纳斯索克吗?
Sure. Cured polio.
被治愈的小儿麻痹症患者
Ever heard of Albert Einstein?
听过爱因斯坦吗?
How about Gerald Lambeau? Ever heard of him?
杰洛蓝勃呢?  听过吗?
No.
没有
Thank you Tim.
谢谢
So who won the bet?
谁赌赢了
I did.
我赢了
This isn't about me Sean.
这不是我的事
I'm nothing compared to this young man.
我跟这年轻人比不算什么
You ever hear of Gerald Lambeau?
你听过杰洛蓝勃吗?
In 1905 there were hundreds of professors renown for their study of the universe.
在1905年有许多以研究宇宙闻名的教授
But it was a 26- year- old Swiss patent clerk...
但改变世界的却是个...
doing physics in his spare time who changed the world.
趁闲暇时研究物理的26岁办事员
Can you imagine if Einstein would have given that up...
你可以想像如果爱因斯坦...
just to get drunk with his buddies in Vienna every night.
每天都喝得烂醉的话会怎样?
We all would have lost something.
我们都会失去一些东西
Tim would never have heard of him.
而提米绝不会听过他
Pretty dramatic Gerry.
非常戏剧化
No it isn't Sean.
不是
This boy has that gift.
这孩子有天赋
He just doesn't got the direction but we can give that to him.
他只是没方向  我们该给他
Hey Gerry in the 1960s...
在60年代曾有一个...
there was a young man graduated from University of Michigan.
密西根大学毕业的年轻人
Did some brilliant work in mathematics.
他的数学很出色
Specifically bounded harmonic functions.
特别是有界集函数
Then he went on to Berkeley. He was assistant professor. Showed amazing potential.
他到柏克莱当助教  潜力惊人
Then he moved to Montana and he blew the competition away.
然后在蒙大拿州赢得竞赛
Yeah so who was he?
好  他是谁?
Ted Kaczynski.
泰德卡辛斯基
Haven't heard of him.
没听过
Hey Timmy!
提米
Who's Ted Kaczynski?
谁是泰德卡辛斯基?
Unabomber.
邮包炸弹狂
That's exactly what I'm talking about. We gotta give this kid direction.
那就是我说的  他需要方向
He can contribute to the world and we can help him do that.
他能贡献世人  我们能帮他
Direction's one thing. Manipulation's another.
方向是一回事  操纵是另一回事
We have to let him find.
你要让他自己发掘
I'm not sitting at home every night...
尚恩  我不是每晚坐在家里...
twisting my mustache and hatching a plan to ruin this boy's life!
策划怎么摧毁他的人生!
I was doing advanced mathematics when I was 18...
我18岁就会做高等数学...
and it still took me over 20 years to do something worthy of a Field's medal.
20年后才得到菲尔德奖章
Maybe he doesn't want what you want.
也许他不想照你的想法去做
There's more to life than a fuckin' Field's medal.
人生不只是一个他妈的奖章
This is too important Sean and it's above personal rivalry.
这太重要了  要超越个人立场
Wait a minute. Let's talk about the boy.
等等  我们谈的是这孩子
Why don't we give him time to figure out what he wants?
为何不给他时间想清楚要什么?
That's a wonderful theory Sean. It worked wonders for you didn't it?
很棒的理论  可为你创造奇迹
Yeah it did you arrogant fuckin' prick!
对  你这自负的混蛋!
Oh I'm sorry.
我很遗憾
I'm sorry that I came here today. I came here out of courtesy.
很遗憾我来了  我是出于好意
I wanted to keep you in the loop.
我想让你参与这件事
Nice to be in the loop.
我很高兴能够参与
The boy's in a meeting right now I set up for him over at McNeil.
他此刻正在我安排的面谈中
Well Will I'm not exactly sure what you mean.
威尔  我不清楚你的意思
We've already offered you a position.
我们已经给你职位了
Nobody in this town works without a retainer guys.
这年头做事没人不拿酬金的
You think you can find somebody who does you have my blessin'.
你们认为找得到  我祝福你们
But I think we all know that person is not gonna represent you as well as I can.
但没有人可以像我做得那么好
Will our offer is $84  000 a year.
我们已给你年薪八万四加福利
Retainer! Retainer.
酬金
You want us to give you cash right now?
你是要我们现在给你现金?
Whoa- ho- ho. Easy...Now I didn't say that.
慢点  我没那么说
Allegedly your situation for you.
但我口袋里如果有两百块
Would be concurrently improved if I had...$200 in my back pocket right now.
你们的处境会同时获得改善
I don't think I can...Larry?
我没有  赖瑞
I've got $73.
我有73块
Will you take a check?
你收支票吗?
Let me tell you somethin'. You're suspect.
你们这种举止相当可疑
Yeah you.
对  你们
I don't know what your reputation is in this town
我不知道你们的声誉怎样
but after the shit you tried to pull today you can bet I'll be lookin' into you.
但耍这种花招  我一定会调查
Now any business we have heretofore
关于我们未来的合作
you can speak with my aforementioned attorney.
请和我的律师谈
Good day gentlemen.
再见  在那天到来前
And until that day comes keep your ear to the grindstone.
拼命干活吧
How's it goin'?
怎么样?
Fine.
很好
Good.
好
Want some help?
要帮忙吗?
No!
不要!
Come on. Give me one little peek and we'll go to the batting cages.
给我看一下  我们要去练球场
No. It is actually important that I learn this.
我一定要念这个
It's really important...
真的很重要...
to me okay?
对我而言
All right.
好吧
Why don't we just hang out here all day?
那就在这边待一整天
Yes why don't we?
有何不可
All right Mr. Nosey Parker.
好  多管闲事先生
Seeing as you're intent on breaking my balls...
既然你打算烦我...
let me ask you a question.
让我问你一个问题
All right.
好
Do you have a photographic memory?
你有影像记忆力吗?
I don't know. I just kind of remember.
不知道  我就是记得
I mean how do you remember your phone number? You just do.
好比你可以记得你的电话号码
Have you studied organic chemistry?
你念过有机化学吗?
A little bit.
一点点
Oh just for fun?
为了好玩?
Yeah for kicks.
对  为了找乐趣
Yeah it's so much fun studying organic chemistry. Are you mad?
念有机化学会有趣  你疯啦
Have you completely lost your mind?
你精神失常吗?
Nobody studies it for fun.
没人会为了好玩念化学
It's not a necessity especially for someone like you.
尤其对你这种人而言根本没必要
Someone like me?
我这种人?
Someone who divides their time fairly evenly between batting cages and bars.
时间分配给练球场和酒吧的人
I would hardly say it was a necessity.
人家不会说那是必要的
You know there are very smart people here at Harvard.
哈佛有很聪明的人
Even they have to study because this is really hard.
但他们都得付出努力才能学会
And yet... you do it so easily. I don't understand.
你却简单地做到了  我不懂
I don't understand how your mind works.
我不懂你的大脑怎么运作
Did you play the piano?
你弹钢琴吗?
I want to talk about this.
别转移话题
No I'm trying to explain it to you. Do you play the piano?
我跟你解释嘛  你会弹吗?
Yeah a bit.
一点点
So when you look at a piano you see Mozart.
好  你看着钢琴就看到莫札特
I see "Chopsticks."
我看到筷子
All right well Beethoven okay? He looked at a piano
好  贝多芬  他一看到钢琴
and it just made sense to him. He could just play.
很自然地就会弹
So what are you saying? You play the piano?
你是说你会弹琴?
Not a lick. I look at a piano...
根本不会  望着钢琴...
I see a bunch of keys three pedals and a box of wood.
我只看到琴键  踏板和木头
But Beethoven Mozart...They saw it. They could just play.
但贝多芬  莫扎特就会弹
I couldn't paint you a picture. I probably can't hit the ball out of Fenway.
我不会画画  连球都打不好
And I can't play the piano.
我也不会弹琴
But you can do my O- chem paper in under an hour.
但你会一小时内做好化学作业
Right. Well I mean when it came to stuff like that I could always just play.
对  我就是会那种东西
That's the best I can explain it.
我只能解释到这样
Come here. I have to tell you something.
来  我有话告诉你
I have to tell you something.
我跟你讲一件事
It's not fair.
不公平
What's not fair? What?
什么不公平?
I've been here for four years.
我在这边四年了
And I've only just found you.
现在才发现你
Well you found me.
起码你还是发现我啦
Are you awake?
你醒着吗?
No.
睡了
Yes you are.
你没睡
Will come to California with me.
跟我一起去加州
What?
什么?
I want you to come to California with me.
我要你跟我去加州
You sure about that?
你确定吗?
Oh yeah.
确定
Yeah but how do you know?
你怎么知道?
I don't know.
不晓得
I just know.
我就是知道
Yeah but how do you know?
但你怎么会知道?
I know because I feel it.
我知道  因为我感觉到
Because that's a really serious thing you're saying.
你说的是很严肃的事
You could be in California next week...
下礼拜到了加州...
and you might find out something about me you don't like.
你可能会发现不喜欢我的地方
Maybe you wish you hadn't said that...
你会希望你没说过这些话...
but you know it's such a serious thing you can't take it back.
但这是无法收回的事
Now I'm stuck in California with someone that doesn't really want to be with me...
于是我跟不爱我的人困在加州...
just wish they had a take- back.
她却希望一切能收回
A what? What's a take- back?
什么?  什么是收回?
I don't want a take- back.
我不想收回
I just want you to come to California with me.
我只要你跟我去加州
Well I can't go to California with you so...
我不能去加州
Why not?
为什么?
Well one because I got a job here.
一是因为我在这边有工作
And two because I live here.
二是因为我住这边
Look um if you don't love me you should just tell me.
你不爱我就该告诉我
I'm not sayin' I don't love you.
我没说不爱你
Then why? Why won't you come? What are you so scared of?
那为什么不去?  你怕什么?
What am I so scared of?
我怕什么?
Well what aren't you scared of?
你不怕什么?
You live in this safe little world where no one challenges you...
你活在没人挑战的世界里...你怕要做改变你的事情
Don't tell me about my world. Don't tell me about my world.
别教我  我的世界怎么样
You just want to have your little fling with the guy from the other side of town.
你只是想跟低下阶层搞一下
Then you're gonna go off to Stanford.
然后到斯坦福
You're gonna marry some rich prick who your parents will approve of...
你会嫁给有钱的混蛋
and just sit around with the other trust fund babies and talk about how you went slummin' too once.
跟其他富家女说你到过贫民窟
Why are you saying this?
你在说什么?
What is your obsession with this money?
你为何这么在乎钱?
My father died when I was 13 and I inherited this money.
我十三岁丧父  继承家产
You don't think every day I wake up and I wish I could give it back.
我每天醒来都希望能还给他
That I would give it back in a second
只要能让我多陪他一天
if it meant I could have one more day with him.
我会马上还给他  但我不能
But I can't and that's my life and I deal with it.
那是我的人生  我面对它
So don't put your shit on me when you're the one that's afraid.
别把你的害怕推到我身上
I'm afraid? What am I afraid of? What the fuck am I afraid of?
我怕?  我他妈的怕什么?
You're afraid of me. You're afraid that I won't love you back.
你怕我  怕我不爱你
You know what? I'm afraid too.
你知道吗?  我也怕
But fuck it I want to give it a shot. At least I'm honest with you.
但我想试试看  起码我诚实
I'm not honest with you?
难道我对你不诚实?
No what about your 12 brothers?
不  你的十二个哥哥呢?
No you're not going. You're not leaving.
你不能走  不准离开
What do you want to know? That I don't have 12 brothers?
你想知道什么?  我没哥哥?
That I'm a fuckin' orphan?
我是个他妈的孤儿?
- You don't want to hear that.  - I didn't know that.
- 你不会想听的  - 我并不晓得
You don't want to hear I got fuckin' cigarettes put out on me when I was little.
你不会想听我童年被香烟烧
I didn't know that.
我不晓得
That this isn't fuckin' surgery. The motherfucker stabbed me.
那不是手术  那混蛋刺伤我
You don't want to hear that shit Skylar!
你不会想听这种事!
Don't tell me you want that shit!
别跟我说你想知道!
I do want to hear that. I want to help you.
我想听  因为我想帮你
Help me? What the fuck?
帮我?  什么鬼东西?
What do I got a fuckin' sign on my back that says "Save me"?
我脸上有写着请救我吗?
Do I look like I need that?
我像要人救的样子吗?
No I just want to be with you...I love you.
我想跟你在一起...我爱你
Don't bullshit me!
别耍我
Don't bullshit me! Don't you fuckin' bullshit me!
别他妈的耍我
I love you.
我爱你
I want to hear you say that you don't love me.
我要听你说你不爱我
Because if you say that...then I won't call you...
那么我就不再打电话给你...
and I won't be in your life.
不再出现在你的生命里
I don't love you.
我不爱你
Most people never get to see how brilliant they can be.
很多人都无从得知自己的天赋
They don't find teachers that believe in them.
因为找不到相信他们的老师
They get convinced they're stupid.
于是他们深信自己很笨
I hope you appreciate what he's doing
希望你能感激他所做的
because I've seen how much he enjoys working with you
我知道他很喜欢跟你合作
not against you.
我没有反对你
Hello Will.
你好  威尔
Tom can you get us some coffee?
汤姆  拿点咖啡来
Sure.
好
Now let's see.
好  我看看
Good. This is correct.
很好  正确
I see you used Maclaurin here.
你用了"麦罗伦"
Yeah I don't know what you call it but...
我不知道叫什么
This can't be right.
这样不对
This would be very embarrassing.
这会很难堪
Did you ever consider...
你是否想过...
I'm pretty sure it's right.
我确信是对的
Hey look can we do this at Sean's office from now on?
以后能在尚恩的办公室做吗?
Because I got to knock off work to come here and the commute is killin' me.
我得放下工作过来  坐车很烦
Yeah sure. Did you think of the possibility...
好  可不可能...
That's right. It's right. Just take it home with you.
它是对的  带回家吧
What happened at the McNeil meeting?
麦尼尔的面谈怎么了?
I couldn't go. I had a date.
我去不了  我有约会
So I sent my chief negotiator.
所以我派我的谈判代表去
On your own time you can do whatever you like Will.
你自己的时间爱干嘛随你
But when I set up a meeting with my associates
但我安排的会谈
and you don't show up it reflects poorly on me.
你没出现会让我丢脸
Then don't set up any more meetings.
好  那就别安排了
I won't. I'll cancel 'em.
我不会  我会取消
I'll give you a job myself. I just wanted you to see what was out there.
我会亲自给你工作
Maybe I don't want to spend the rest of my fuckin' life explainin' shit to people.
或许我不想一辈子做解说员
I think you could show me some appreciation.
但你可以表示感激吧
A little appreciation? Do you know how easy this is for me?
感激?  你知道这多容易吗?
Do you have any fuckin' idea how easy this is? This is a fuckin' joke.
你知道吗?  别他妈的说笑了
I'm sorry you can't do this...I really am...
我很遗憾你不会解  真的
Because I wouldn't have to fuckin' sit here and watch you fumble around and fuck it up.
我不想坐在这儿看你摸索
Then you'd have more time to sit around and get drunk instead wouldn't you?
这样你就会有更多的时间喝醉?
You're right. This is probably a total waste of my time.
没错  这浪费我的时间
You're right Will.
你说得对
I can't do this proof
我解不出来
but you can. And when it comes to that
但你会  说到这个
it's only about just a handful of people in the world who can tell the difference between you and me.
只有少数人看出你我的差别
But I'm one of them.
我是其中之一
Sorry.
我很遗憾
Yeah so am I.
我也是
Most days I wish I never met you
我常希望没遇到你
because then I could sleep at night.
这样我夜里就能睡得着
I didn't have to walk around with the knowledge that there was someone like you out there.
不用惦记有个像你这样的人
I didn't have to watch you throw it all away.
我不必看你糟蹋天赋
Bill hold it.
比尔  等等
Did you hear that?
听到没?
Morgan!
摩根!
If you're watchin' pornos in my mom's room again
如你还敢在我妈房里看A片
I'm gonna give you a fuckin' beatin'!
我就揍扁你
What's up fellas?
怎么了?
Morgan why don't you jerk off in your own fuckin' house. That's fuckin' filthy.
要打手枪在你家里打  脏死了
I don't have a V.C.R. in my house.
我家没录影机
I don't care it.
他妈的我不管
Come on. Not in my glove.
你不会用我手套打手枪吧
I didn't use the glove.
我没用手套
That's my Little League glove.
那是我的小联盟手套
What do you want me to do?
你要我怎么做
I mean what's wrong with you? You'll hump a baseball glove?
你怎么搞的?  操棒球手套啊?
I- I just used it for cleanup.
我没有  我用它清干净
Stop jerkin' off in my mother's room.
别在我妈房里打手枪了
Is there another V.C.R. in the house?
这屋里还有别台录影机吗?
It's just sad bro.
真可悲
So why do you think I should work for the National Security Agency?
我为什么该为国安局做事?
Well you'd be working on the cutting edge.
你将研究尖端科技
You'd be exposed to the kind of technology you wouldn't see anywhere else
接触别处看不到的科技
because we've classified it.
因为都已列为机密
Superstring theory chaos math advanced algorithms.
混沌数学  高级算法...
Code breaking.
破解密码
That's one aspect of what we do.
那是其中一个层面
Oh come on. That is what you do.
得了  那就是你们做的事
You guys handle 80% of the intelligence workload.
你们处理八成的情报量
You're seven times the size of the C.I.A.
是中情局的七倍大
We don't like to brag about that Will but you're exactly right.
我们不喜欢自夸  但你说对了
So the way I see it the question isn't:"Why should you work for the N.S.A.?"
问题不是"你干嘛为国安局做事"
The question is: "Why shouldn't you?"
而是"你为何不做?"
Why shouldn't I work for the N.S.A.?
我为何不为国安局做事?
That's a tough one
很难的问题
but I'll take a shot. Say I'm workin' at the N.S.A.
让我想想  若我做了
and somebody puts a code on my desk. Something no one else can break.
国安局会给我破解不了的密码
Maybe I take a shot at it and maybe I break it.
或许我试了  也破解了
I'm real happy with myself because I did my job well.
我很满意  因为表现良好
But maybe that code...
但也许那个密码...
was the location of some rebel army in North Africa or Middle East.
是位于北非或中东的叛军位置
Once they have that location they bomb the village where the rebels are hidin'.
他们发现后轰炸叛军藏身地
Fifteen hundred people that I never met never had no problem with get killed.
陌生的一千五百人因此丧命
Now the politicians are saying "Send in the Marines to secure the area  "
然后政客派特战部队防守该区
'cause they don't give a shit.
他们才不在乎
It won't be their kid over there gettin' shot
因为被射杀的不会是他们的子女
just like it wasn't them when their number got called 'cause they were in the National Guard.
因为他们都加入了后备部队
It'll be some kid from Southie over there takin' shrapnel in the ass.
而在那边中弹的南区孩子
He comes back to find the plant he used to work at...
回国后发现他以前工作的工厂...
got exported to the country he got back from
被移转到他去打仗的国家
and the guy who put the shrapnel in his ass got his old job...
害他中弹的敌人抢了他的饭碗
'cause he'll work for 15 cents a day and no bathroom breaks.
因为那儿的人一天工资不到一元
Meanwhile he realizes the only reason he was over there in the first place...
最后他发现他会上战场...
was so we could install a government that would sell us oil at a good price.
只是为了得到该国的廉价原油
Of course the oil companies used a skirmish over there
好让石油公司利用战争恐慌
to scare up domestic oil prices. A cute little ancillary benefit for them.
抬高国内油价  小赚一番
but it ain't helpin' my buddy at 2.50 a gallon.
但两块五一加仑有个屁用
They're takin' their sweet time bringin' the oil of course.
他们得花时间把石油运回国
Maybe they even took the liberty to hire an alcoholic skipper
或许还请了一个酗酒船长
who likes to drink martinis and fuckin' play slalom with the icebergs.
他爱喝马丁尼  跟冰山玩滑雪
It ain't too long till he hits one spills the oil...
不久他撞上冰山  原油外漏...
and kills all the sea life in the North Atlantic.
杀光北大西洋的海洋生物
So now my buddy's out of work he can't afford to drive
现在我朋友失业  也开不起车
so he's walkin' to the fuckin' job interviews...
他走路去面谈  很难受
which sucks because the shrapnel in his ass is givin' him chronic hemorrhoids.
因为炮弹片让你慢性出血
Meanwhile he's starvin' 'cause every time he tries to get a bite to eat
他很饿  因为每次想吃东西
the only blue plate special they're servin' is North Atlantic scrod with Quaker State.
唯一的特餐是北大西洋鳕鱼
So what did I think?
所以  我会怎么想?
I'm holdin' out for somethin' better.
我有更好的点子
I figure fuck it. While I'm at it why not just shoot my buddy
干  我干脆射杀我朋友算了
take his job give it to his sworn enemy hike up gas prices.
把工作给敌人  提高油价
Bomb a village club a baby seal
轰炸村庄  打死小海豹
hit the hash pipe and join the National Guard?
吸食大麻  加入后备部队
I can be elected president.
我还可因此被选为总统
You feel like you're alone?
你感觉孤单吗?
What?
什么?
Do you have a soul mate?
你有心灵伴侣吗?
Do I have a...Define that.
我有...?  说清楚点
Somebody who challenges you.
能够和你匹敌的人
Uh Chuckie.
我有查克
No Chuckie's family. He'd lie down in fuckin' traffic for you.
不  查克是你的家人
I'm talking about someone who opens up things for you touches your soul.
我讲的是触动你心灵的人
I got...I got...
我有...
Who?
谁?
I got plenty.
有很多
Well name 'em.
说出来
Shakespeare Nietzsche Frost...
莎士比亚  尼采  佛斯特...
O'Connor Kant Pope Locke.
奥康纳  康德  洛克.
That's great. They're all dead.
很棒  他们都死了
Not to me they're not.
对我而言  他们没死
You don't have a lot of dialogue with them.
没死?  你无法和他们对谈
You can't give back to them Will.
你不能回应他们
Not without some serious smelling salts and a heater.
除非你有仙丹
That's what I'm saying.
对  那就是我所说的
You'll never have that kind of relationship in a world...
如果你不踏出第一步...
where you're always afraid to take the first step
你绝不会有那种关系
because all you see is every negative thing ten miles down the road.
因为你只看到负面的事
You gonna take the professor's side on this?
你要摆出教授架子了?
Don't give me a line of shit. No.
少跟我来这套  没有
I didn't want the job.
我不想做那个工作
It's not about the job. I don't care if you work for the government.
我不管你是否为政府工作
But you can do anything you want. You are bound by nothing.
但你能随心所欲  不受束缚
What are you passionate about? What do you want?
你热爱什么?  想要什么?
There are guys who work their entire life layin' brick...
有人一辈子砌砖...
so their kids have a chance at the opportunities you have here.
为了让孩子拥有像你现在的机会
I didn't ask for this.
我可没要求这机会
No. You were born with it
不  你生来就有
So don't cop out behind: "I didn't ask for this."
别逃避说你没要求
What do you mean cop out? What's wrong with layin' brick?
什么叫逃避?  砌砖哪里不对?
Nothing.
没有
There's nothin' wrong. That's somebody's home I'm buildin'.
没什么不对  我盖房子...
Right. My dad laid brick okay?
对  我爸砌砖  好吗?
Busted his ass so I could have an education.
他拼命干活让我受教育
Exactly. That's an honorable profession.
没错  那是可敬的行业
What's wrong with fixin' somebody's car?
修车哪不对?
Someone will get to work the next day because of me. That's honor in that.
我让人能上班  这是很光荣的事
Yeah there is Will. There is honor in that.
是的  是很光荣
There's honor in takin' that 40- minute train ride...
搭40分钟火车让大学生...
so those college kids could come in in the morning and their floors are clean.
上课有干净的地板...
And their wastebaskets are empty. That's real work.
整洁的桌椅也很可敬
That's right.
对
And that's honorable.
对  是很可敬
I'm sure that's why you took that job. I mean for the honor of it.
相信你是为了这份荣耀才做的
I just have a little question here.
我只是有个小问题
You could be a janitor anywhere.
你到哪里都能做工友
Why did you work at the most prestigious technical college in the whole fuckin' world?
为何挑中一流的科技学府?
Why did you sneak around at night and finish other people's formulas...
夜里偷偷地解算...
that only one or two people in the world could do and then lie about it?
世上只有两个人会的方程式?
'Cause I don't see a lot of honor in that Will.
我看不到其中的荣耀
So what do you really wanna do?
你真正想做什么?
I wanna be a shepherd.
我想当牧羊人
Really?
真的?
I wanna move up to Nashua get a nice little spread get some sheep and tend to them.
我想搬到纳旭买块地放羊
Maybe you should go do that.
也许你该那么做
What?
什么?
You know if you're gonna jerk off why don't you just do it at home with a moist towel?
要自慰回家弄条湿毛巾搞
You're chuckin' me?
你在赶我?
Yeah get the fuck outta here.
对  出去
No no no time's not up yet.
不  时间还没到
- Yeah it is.  - I'm not leavin'. No.
- 确实没到  - 我不走  不
You're not gonna answer you're wastin' my time.
你不回答我问题  浪费我时间
I thought we were friends.
我以为我们是朋友
Playtime's over okay?
游戏时间结束了
Why are you kickin' me out?
你为什么赶我走?
You're lecturin' me on life?
你想教我人生大道理?
Look at you you fuckin' burnout.
看看你  糟老头
What winds your clock?
是什么让你过下去?
Workin' with you.
跟你合作
Where's your soul mate?
你的心灵伴侣在哪?
You wanna talk about soul mates? Where is she?
你要谈心灵伴侣  她在哪?
Dead.
死了
That's right. She's fuckin' dead.
对  她已经他妈的死了
She fuckin' dies and you just cash in your chips and you walk away?
你就不敢再为人生下赌注了?
At least I played a hand.
起码我玩过一把
You played a hand and you lost. You lost a big fuckin' hand.
那你输了  输得很惨
Some people will lose a big hand like that and have the sack to ante up again.
有些人输那么惨还会再下注
Look at me. What do you wanna do?
看着我  你想要什么?
You and your bullshit.
你和你那些屁话
You got a bullshit answer for everybody.
每个人你都有狗屁答案
But I ask you a very simple question and you can't give me a straight answer
却答不出来这么简单的问题
because you don't know.
因为你不知道
I'll see ya Bo- peep.
再见  躲猫猫
Fuck you.
去你的
You're the shepherd.
你是牧羊人
Shepherd. White little prick.
牧羊人  混蛋
I just wanted to you know um call you up uh before you left um...
趁你还没走打电话给你
I've been takin' all these jobs interviews and stuff
我正在谈工作
so I'm not gonna be just a construction worker.
我不会只当营造工人
Well you know I never really cared about that.
你知道我并不在乎
Yeah.
是的
I love you.
我爱你
Will?
威尔?
You take care.
你保重
Bye.
再见
Will come on. Will!
威尔
Will that's it! We're done!
好了  做完了!
I'm sitting in your office and the boy isn't here.
我在你办公室  那孩子没来
Well it's ten past 5:00.
十点五分了
An hour and ten minutes late.
迟到一小时十分
Well if he doesn't show up and I file a report saying he wasn't here...
他不出现我就提交报告
and he goes back to jail he won't be on my conscience.
他去坐牢我也不会愧疚的
Okay. Fine.
好  很好
What's up?
怎么了?
Thanks.
谢谢
Ah! God that's good.
真爽
So how's your lady?
你马子怎么样?
Ah she's gone.
她走了
Gone? Gone where?
走?  走去哪里?
Med school. Medical school in California.
医学院  加州的医学院
Really?
真的?
When was this?
几时的事?
It was like a week ago.
一礼拜前
That sucks.
好烂
Yeah.
对
So uh when are you done with those meetings?
那些会谈几时搞完?
I think the week after I'm 21.
过了21岁的那个星期
They gonna hook ya up with a job or what?
是吗?  他们要给你工作吗?
Yeah fuckin' sit in a room and do long division for the next 50 years.
往后50年要做无聊的算术
Nah probably make some nice bank though.
可能会攒不少钱
I'm gonna be a fuckin' lab rat.
我会成为他妈的实验室老鼠
Better than this shit. Way outta here.
好过这鬼东西  离开这里
What do I want a way outta here for?
干嘛走?
I mean I'm gonna fuckin' live here the rest of my life.
我下辈子都要住这儿
You know be neighbors. You know have little kids.
我们当邻居  我们会当爸爸
Fuckin' take 'em to Little League together up Foley Field.
一起带他们打小联盟
Look you're my best friend so don't take this the wrong way.
你是我的死党  所以别误会
But in 20 years if you're still livin' here
但20年后你如果还住在这儿
comin' over to my house to watch the Patriots games
到我家看球赛
still workin' construction I'll fuckin' kill ya.
还在盖房子  我会他妈的杀了你
That's not a threat. That's a fact. I'll fuckin' kill ya.
那不是恐吓  我会宰了你
What the fuck are you talkin' about?
你在胡扯什么?
Look you got something none of us have.
你拥有我们没有的天赋
Oh come on!  Why is it always this?
拜托  为何大家都这么说?
I fuckin' owe it to myself to do this or that. What if I don't want to?
难道是我对不起自己吗?
No no no. Fuck you. You don't owe it to yourself.
不  你没有对不起自己
You owe it to me
是你对不起我
'cause tomorrow I'm gonna wake up and I'll be 50
因为我明天醒来五十岁了
and I'll still be doin' this shit. That's all right. That's fine.
还在干这种事  无所谓
I mean you're sittin' on a winnin' lottery ticket.
而你已拥有百万奖券
You're too much of a pussy to cash it in and that's bullshit.
却窝囊的不敢兑现  狗屁
'Cause I'd do fuckin' anything to have what you got.
我会不惜一切交换你所拥有的
So would any of these fuckin' guys.
其他这些人也是
Be an insult to us if you're still here in 20 years.
你再待20年是侮辱我们
Hangin' around here is a fuckin' waste of your time.
窝在这里是浪费你时间
You don't know that.
你懂什么?
I don't know that?
我不懂?
No. You don't know that.
你不懂
Oh I don't know that. Let me tell you what I do know.
我告诉你我懂什么
Every day I come by your house and I pick you up.
我每天到你家接你
We go out and have a few drinks and few laughs and it's great.
我们出去喝酒笑闹  那很棒
You know what the best part of my day is?
但我一天中最棒的时刻
It's for about ten seconds:
只有十秒
from when I pull up to the curb and when I get to your door.
从停车场到你家门口
'Cause I think maybe I'll get up there and I'll knock on the door and you won't be there.
每次我敲门都希望你不在了
No "good- bye  " no "see ya later." No nothing.
不说再见  什么都没有
You just left.
就这么走了
I don't know much but I know that.
我懂得不多  但我很清楚
This is a disaster Sean. I brought you in here...
真是乱来  我让你参与...
because I wanted you to help me with the boy not to run him out.
是要你帮这孩子  不是赶走他
I know what I'm doing with the boy.
我知道怎么应付他
I don't care if you have a rapport with the boy!
我不管你跟他有什么默契
I don't care if you have a few laughs even at my expense.
我不在乎你们花我的钱开心
But don't you dare undermine what I'm trying to do here.
但你敢破坏我的事看看
Undermine?
破坏?
This boy is at a fragile point right now.
这孩子目前很脆弱
I do understand. He is at a fragile point.
我了解他很脆弱  好吗?
He's got problems.
他还有些问题
What problems does he have?
他有什么问题?
That he's better off as a janitor in jail?
当工友或坐牢会比较好吗?
Better hanging out with a bunch of retarded gorillas?
跟一群智障在一起会比较好吗?
Why do you think he does that?
你想他为什么那么做?
You have any fuckin' clue why?
你晓得为什么吗?
He can handle the problems.
他能应付问题
He can handle the work. He obviously handled you.
应付工作  显然也应付你了
Listen to me.
听我说
Why is he hiding? Why doesn't he trust anybody?
他为何躲避?  为何不信任人?
Because the first thing that happened to him
因为他的遭遇
he was abandoned by the people who were supposed to love him the most.
他被应该爱他的人遗弃
Don't give me that Freudian crap.
别跟我讲佛洛伊德的屁话
Why does he hang out with those retarded gorillas as you call them?
他为什么跟你所谓的智障混?
Because any one of them if he asked them to
因为如果他叫他们扁你
would take a bat to your head. That's called loyalty.
他们会照办  那叫做义气
Yeah that's very touching.
是喔  很感人
Who's he handling?
他应付谁了?
He pushes people away before they have a chance to leave him.
他在别人离开之前先赶人走
It's a defense mechanism all right?
那是防卫心理  好吗?
For 20 years he's been alone because of that.
他因此孤独了20年
If you push him right now it's gonna be the same thing all over again.
你现在逼他  事情会重演
I'm not gonna let that happen to him.
我不会让他重蹈覆辙
Don't you do that.
别那么做
What?
什么?
Don't infect him with the idea that it's okay to quit that it's okay to be a failure.
别让他认为放弃或失败没关系
Because it's not okay Sean!
绝对有关系!
And if you're angry at me for being successful for being what you could have been...
如果你是气我成功...
I'm not angry at you.
我没气你
Oh yes you're angry at me.
你有  你憎恶我
You resent me but I'm not gonna apologize for any success I've had.
我不会因为成功向你赔不是
You're angry at me for doing what you could have done!
你气我做到你本来能做到的事
But ask yourself Sean...Ask yourself...
你扪心自问
if you want Will to feel that way...
你要威尔有那种感受?
if you want him to feel like a failure?
你要他感觉像失败者?
You arrogant shit!
你这个自大狂!
That's why I don't come to the goddamn reunions
我不去同学会的原因
'cause I can't stand that look in your eye.
是因为受不了你的眼神
That condescending embarrassed look.
那种屈尊难堪的眼神
You think I'm a failure. I know who I am.
你认为我失败  我有自知之明
I'm proud of what I do.
我为自己感到骄傲
It was a conscious choice.
那是自觉的选择
I didn't fuck up!
我没搞砸!
And you and your cronies think I'm some sort of pity case.
你和你朋友认为我很可怜
You and your kiss- ass chorus...
你和你那些狗屁课程
following you around going "The Field's medal!"
你老是提自己的菲尔德奖章...
Why are you still so fuckin' afraid of failure?
你怎么还是这么怕失败?
It's about my medal isn't it?
你是嫉妒我有奖章吗?
Oh God I could go home and get it for you. You can have it.
天哪  我回家拿给你  送给你好了
Oh please don't.
拜托不要
Shove the medal up your fuckin' ass all right?
把奖章塞进你妈的屁眼里
'Cause I don't give a shit about your medal
因为我不在乎你的奖章
because I knew you before you were a mathematical god
因为我在你还没当上数学之神前就认识你了
when you were pimple- faced and homesick...
早在你满脸青春痘  思乡...
and didn't know what side of the bed to piss on.
不知要尿在床的那一头的时候
Yeah you were smarter than me then and you're smarter than me now.
是  你过去现在都比我聪明
So don't blame me for how your life turned out.
你人生变成这样别怪我
I don't blame you! It's not about you!
我没怪你!  这跟你无关!
You mathematical dick! It's about the boy!
你这数学混球!  是关于那孩子!
He's a good kid! And I won't see you...
他是好孩子!  我不会看着你...
fuck him up like you're tryin' to fuck up me right now.
像现在糟蹋我般糟蹋他
I won't see you make him feel like a failure too!
让他也感觉是失败者!
He won't be a failure!
他不会失败!
But if you push him! If you ride him!
但你如果逼他!
I am what I am today because I was pushed and because I learned to push myself.
我能有今天成就是逼出来的
He's not you! You get that!
他不是你!  你懂吗!
I can come back.
我待会再来
No come in. Uh I was just leaving.
不  进来  我正要走
A lot of that stuff goes back a long way between me and him.
他和我之间的陈年往事
You know. Not about you.
跟你无关
What is that?
那是什么?
This is your file.
你的档案
I have to send it back to the judge for evaluation.
我要送回去给法官评估
Oh. Hey you're not gonna fail me are you?
你不会让我失败吧?
What's it say?
里面怎么写?
Wanna read it?
你想看吗?
Why?
为什么?
Have you had any uh experience with that?
你有过那种经验吗?
Twenty years of counseling.
20年的辅导
Yeah I've seen some pretty awful shit.
我看过很惨的事
I mean have you had any experience with that?
你有那方面的经验吗?
Personally?
个人的?
Yeah.
是的
Yeah I have.
我有
It sure ain't good.
肯定不好
My father was an alcoholic. Mean fuckin' drunk.
我爸是酒鬼  烂醉如泥
He'd come home hammered lookin' to whale on somebody.
他喝醉回家就想打人
So I'd provoke him so he wouldn't go after my mother and little brother.
我激怒他以保护妈妈和弟弟
Interesting nights when he wore his rings.
他若晚上带工具回来就精彩了
He used to just put a wrench a stick and a belt on the table.
他把扳手  棍子和皮带摆桌上
Just say "Choose."
然后说"选一个"
Well I gotta go with the belt there.
我会挑皮带
I used to go with the wrench.
我通常挑扳手
Why the wrench?
为什么是扳手?
'Cause fuck him that's why.
因为是"操他的"
Your foster father?
你养父?
Yeah. So uh what is it.
对  怎么样?
Like Will has an attachment disorder? Is it all that stuff?
是不是威尔有"依附情结"?
Fear of abandonment?
害怕被遗弃?
Is that why I broke up with Skylar?
那是我跟史凯兰分手的原因吗?
I didn't know you had.
我不晓得你们分手了
Yeah I did.
分手了
You wanna talk about it?
想谈吗?
No.
不想
Hey Will I don't know a lot.
威尔  我知道的不多
You see this?
但你看到这个没?
All this shit?
这些事
It's not your fault.
不是你的错
Yeah I know that.
是  我知道
Look at me son. It's not your fault.
看着我  孩子  不是你的错
I know.
我知道
No. It's not your fault.
不是你的错
I know.
我知道
No no you don't. It's not your fault.
你不知道  不是你的错
I know.
我知道
It's not your fault.
不是你的错
All right.
好
It's not your fault.
不是你的错
Don't fuck with me all right?
别整我
It's not your fault.
不是你的错
Don't fuck with me Sean not you.
别整我好吗?  不要是你
It's not your fault.
不是你的错
My God...My God! I'm so sorry! My God!
我的天...真对不起
Fuck them okay?
去他们的  好吗?
Can I help you?
有什么事吗?
Yeah I'm Will Hunting. I'm here about a position.
我是威尔杭汀  我来谈工作
Could you just have a seat for a moment?
请坐一下
Which one did you take?
你选择哪一个?
I was over at McNeil.
麦尼尔那边
It's one of the jobs the professor set me up with.
教授帮我安排的工作之一
I haven't told him yet but I went down there and talked to my boss...
我还没告诉他  我和老板谈过...
My new boss. He seemed like a good guy.
新老板人好像不错
Is that what you want?
那是你要的吗?
Yeah you know I think so.
对  我想是吧
Well good for you. Congratulations.
做得好  恭喜
Thanks.
谢谢
Time's up.
时间到了
So that's...So that's it? So we're done?
就这样?  我们结束了
Yeah that's it.
对  就这样
You're done. You're a free man.
你结束了  自由了
Well um I just want you to know Sean that...
我想跟你说  我...
You're welcome Will.
不客气
So you know I hope we keep in touch you know.
希望我们保持联络
Yeah me too.
我也希望
I'll be travelin' around a bit. It'll be a little hard but uh...
我会旅行一阵子  会有点难
I've got an answering machine at the college I'll be checking in with.
不过我有答录机  我会查
So here's the number.
拿着
You call that. I'll get back to you right away.
你打来  我会马上回电话
Yeah you know I figured I'm just gonnan put my money back on the table...
我要再下注...
and see what kind of cards I get.
看这次赌到什么
You do what's in your heart son. You'll be fine.
你跟着心走就没事了
Thank you Sean.
谢谢你  尚恩
Thank you Will.
谢谢你  威尔
Hey does this violate the patient- doctor relationship?
这违反医师病人关系吗?
Naw. Only if you grab my ass.
除非你抓我屁股
Take care.
保重
You too.
你也是
Good luck son.
祝你好运  孩子
Two beers.
两瓶啤酒
What's up? Did you guys go?
你们去了吗?
No. I had to talk him down.
没有  我得劝退他
Why didn't you yoke him?
你怎么不管管他?
Little Morgan's got a lot of scrap to him.
摩根有一堆屁话
People try to whip his ass every week. Fuckin' kid won't back down.
天天有人想扁他  他还不让步
What are you sayin' about me?
讲我什么?
Was I talkin' to you? None of your fuckin' business.
我跟你讲话吗?  干你屁事
Go get me a beer.
帮我弄个啤酒
I ordered two beers!
我叫了两瓶
Hey asshole.
浑蛋
What bitch?
干嘛?  贱货
Happy birthday.
生日快乐
Thought we forgot huh bitch?
以为我们忘了吗?  贱货
- Come on!  - I'm goin'. I'm goin'.
- 我去  - 我去
All right. Who's first?
谁先?
- Come on motherfucker!  - Who's first?
- 来吧混蛋  - 谁先?
Oh Danny boy
丹尼男孩
Here's your present.
你的礼物
Come on bro.
快点
Well we knew you had to get back and forth to Cambridge for your new job.
你的新工作要在剑桥来回
I knew I wasn't gonna fuckin' drive you every day so...
我不会每天载你  所以...
Morgan wanted to get you a "T" pass.
摩根想给你买免票证
That's not what I was sayin'!
我没那么说
- But uh you're 21 now.  - You're legally allowed to drink.
- 但你21岁了  - 可以合法喝酒
So we figured the best thing for ya was a car.
我们想最好的礼物就是车子
How do you like it?
喜欢吗?
This is like...
这是...
It's the ugliest fuckin' car I've ever seen in my life.
我这辈子看过最丑的车
Come on brother.
快  兄弟
How'd you guys do this?
你们怎么弄的?
You know me and Bill scraped together the parts
我和比尔一起搜括零件
and Morgan was out panhandlin' for change every day.
摩根每天出去乞讨零钱
I had the router to do all the bodywork.
车身都是我搞的
Yeah I have a fuckin' job too brother.
弄得他妈的棒呆了
Guy's been up my ass for two years about a job.
他烦了我两年要工作
I had to let him help with the car.
总得让他做帮手
So you finally got a job huh Morgan?
你终于有工作了?  摩根
Yeah had one. Now I'm fucked again.
有过一个  现在又没了
So what is it? A lawn mower? What do ya got?
是什么工作?  除草工人吗?
Me and Bill rebuilt this engine ourselves here.
我和比尔重新打造引擎
It's a good car. The engine's good. Engine's good.
这是辆好车  引擎不错
Happy 21 Will.
生日快乐  威尔
Happy 21 brother.
21岁生日快乐  兄弟
Come on in.
进来
Sean l um...
尚恩  我...
Me too Gerry.
我也是
Yeah. Good.
那就好
I heard you're takin' some time.
听说你要请假
Yeah. Travel a little bit.
对  我想旅行一阵子
Maybe write.
或许写书
So where are you going?
去哪里?
India and China and Baltimore.
印度  中国和巴尔的摩
You know when you'll be back?
你知道几时回来吗?
Oh. I got this flyer the other day.
知道  我前两天收到传单
It says uh class of '72 is having a reunion in six months.
上面说半年后开同学会
Yeah I got one of those too.
是  我也收到一张
Why don't you come? I'll buy ya a drink.
你来吧  我请你喝酒
The drinks at those things are free.
那种场合的酒是免费的
I know Gerry. I was being ironical.
我知道  我在讽刺
How about a drink right now?
现在喝一杯怎么样?
Yeah. It's a good idea.
好啊  好主意
Come on. This one's on me.
走  这杯我请
I got the winner right here pal.
我这边有会中奖的彩票
Yes sir this is the one.
对  就是这张
This is my ticket to paradise.
通往天堂的票
Do you know what the odds are against winning the lottery?
你知道彩券中奖的机率吗?
What? Four to one?
四比一?
About 30 million to one.
三千万比一
I still have a shot you know?
还是有机会
Yes just about as big chance as you being hit by lightning here on the staircase right now.
跟现在被闪电击中的机率一样
It's a possibility too. I mean 32 million. If you look at the size...
那也有可能...
Will!
威尔!
Will?
威尔?
He's not there.
他不在
Sean.
尚恩
If the professor calls about that job.
如果教授问起工作的事
just tell him sorry I had to go see about a girl.
跟他说抱歉  我要去找个女孩
Will.
威尔
Son of a bitch. He stole my line.
这个小混蛋  偷我的?